<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Political Physicist</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/feeds/politics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://politicalphysicist.github.io/</id><updated>2016-06-25T00:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>You Don’t Have to Like Brexit, But You do Have to Live With it</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/you-dont-have-to-like-brexit-but-you-do-have-to-live-with-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-06-25T00:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2016-06-25:you-dont-have-to-like-brexit-but-you-do-have-to-live-with-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, the vote was for Brexit. I am stating this as a fact, not meaning to
place any particular mourning or celebration in it. I can&amp;#8217;t say I&amp;#8217;m a fan of
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. I think it is neoliberal and unaccountable, probably
irredeemably so in both cases. But I take no joy in the outcome of
this vote. The narrative leading to Brexit was not one of building a
better future based on cooperation, without the constant calls for
greater &amp;#8220;competitiveness&amp;#8221;. Instead, it was a narrative of
out-of-control immigration, the interfering outsiders, Britain no
longer being Great thanks to the burdens of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. It was not a
pleasant campaign for those of us on the&amp;nbsp;Left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear: I am a believer in democratic
European federalism. However, I have serious doubts that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; can
ever become such a system, given its extreme democratic deficit. At
best, I think that a set of countries, which would like need to be
lead by Leftist governments, would essentially secede from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; at
once to form some other institution.  More likely,
any such government would be forced out of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; if it tried to
implement a serious Leftist program, long before a coordinated
secession could be achieved. I don&amp;#8217;t think the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; will ever be
a conducive battleground for Leftist&amp;nbsp;ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this leaves us in a depressing state. The exit vote was driven by
right-wing narratives, while staying would have locked us into a neoliberal
framework. I knew this was the choice ahead of us long before the vote
occurred. We were faced only with bad outcomes. Given that, I
won&amp;#8217;t condemn anyone on the Left for their choices, whether they voted
to leave, remain, spoiled their ballot, or abstained. I knew that,
however they voted, Leftists were not motivated by racism or
nationalism but by a genuine concern for building a better world. I knew that,
regardless of the result of the vote, we were going to need to fight
harder than ever to build international solidarity, to develop
coherent policies for a socialist program, to bring the hundreds of
thousands, if not millions, of dispossessed Britons and Europeans into
the struggle for a better&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the vote was for Brexit. We have to accept that. We don&amp;#8217;t have
to like it or agree with it, but we have to accept it. Calling the
people who voted for it stupid, or racists, or saying that you&amp;#8217;re
ashamed to be British isn&amp;#8217;t going to do any good. In fact, it will
only alienate the Brexit voters&amp;#8212;who we&amp;#8217;ll need if the Left is ever to
get elected&amp;#8212;even more. Perhaps today was a defeat for
the Left. Well, the Left has had almost nothing but defeats in this
country (or anywhere else) since 1979, and we know how to keep on going. 
This result will make many things more difficult, but it will make
some things&amp;nbsp;easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Brexit vote happened. We don&amp;#8217;t yet know what the final resolution to
this story will be, but we have to do everything in our power to ensure
that our future outside of the European Union is as just and humane as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="UK"></category><category term="EU"></category><category term="British Politics"></category><category term="Europe"></category><category term="Brexit"></category></entry><entry><title>Greeks Bearing Debts</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/greeks-bearing-debts.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-23T01:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2015-06-23:greeks-bearing-debts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SYRIZA supporters celebrating their election victory in January" src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/syrizaVictory.jpg" /&gt;
Just over five months ago, Greece elected a new government lead by left-wing
party &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; comes out of a radical tradition rejecting both
reformist social democracy and authoritarian communism and was swept to power
on a wave of anti-austerity sentiment. Austerity refers to the massive cuts to
public spending (tending to hurt particularly those on lower incomes) which
Greece has endured over the past five years, along with
the associated policies of deregulation, cuts to the minimum wage, an end to
collective bargaining, and the privatization of anything which actually makes
a profit for the government. These policies have been devastating for Greece,
resulting in a 26% contraction in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt;, ~25% unemployment, over 50% youth
unemployment, and a humanitarian disaster as people can&amp;#8217;t get access to food,
energy, shelter, or basic healthcare.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it is fair to say that Greece did borrow too much money over the years
leading up to the crisis. However, I think it is also fair to say that there
is an inverse relationship between someone&amp;#8217;s culpability for the debt and the
pain which they have experienced under austerity. It is also true that the
Greek state is hopelessly corrupt. That said, of all of the parties represented
in the Hellenic Parliament, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; is probably the one with the greatest
commitment to try to tack&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, none of this is new&amp;#8212;it was all equally the case when &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; was elected
in January. At that time, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; had pledged to end austerity while staying a
part of the Eurozone and refraining from any unilateral actions (i.e. defaulting
on the debt). Given that Greeks overwhelmingly favour staying in the Euro, it
is not surprising that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; would make such a commitment. They insisted that
they would be able to reverse austerity&amp;nbsp;by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immediately implementing the
&lt;a href="http://www.syriza.gr/article/SYRIZA---THE-THESSALONIKI-PROGRAMME.html#.VYjAUnMl_VM"&gt;Thessaloniki Program&lt;/a&gt;
which purported to provide a mild Keynseianism with the resources already
available to the Greek&amp;nbsp;government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renegotiating the debt with Europe, on the basis that austerity clearly was
not leading to growth and was hurting the Eurozone as a whole. Furthermore, they
would point out that there was no way that Greece would ever be able to repay
the debt as the situations currently stands, whether they want to or&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it almost immediately&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; became clear to anyone who was watching with
a remotely level head that this would not be as easy as was claimed. The
leadership of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; are die-hard Europeans who, reportedly, believe in the
European project (European integration which, in reality, means the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and the
Euro) at a deep emotional level. They were thus extremely reluctant to
countenance any sort of break with Europe, even without considering that public
opinion took a similar view. It would thus appear that they genuinely thought
that, if they were to sit down and explain to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; why austerity was
wrong-headed then it would see the light. Now, I certainly would not condemn
giving this a try&amp;#8212;after all, what have they got to loose? But I found it
incredibly hard to believe that they would go into these quixotic negotiations
without even a sketch of an alternative plan to pursue if they&amp;nbsp;failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet that is what seems to be the case. In February, prompted by the
potential collapse of the Greek banking sector, Athens signed a deal with the
European Commission, the European Central Bank, and the International Monetary
Fund (previously called &amp;#8220;the Troika,&amp;#8221; since renamed &amp;#8220;the institutions&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;the
Brussels group&amp;#8221; for reasons of political spin) in order to ensure that the
European Central Bank would keep it afloat. However, this deal represented
a &lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/02/syriza-euro-austerity-troika/"&gt;major retreat&lt;/a&gt;
from their election promises, as it committed them to austerity (with vague
enough language that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; naively hoped that they could wriggle out of it)
and forbade them from passing any legislation which could, in the view of
&amp;#8220;the institutions,&amp;#8221; endanger the Greek &amp;#8220;recovery.&amp;#8221; The worst part of all of this
was that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; leadership tried to portray this as a victory and proof that
it was possible to negotiate a resolution with&amp;nbsp;Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since that time, Greece has not actually seen any of the money that
they were promised from the Troika, as they must first start to implement the
structural adjustments demanded. This has left Athens with very little money
to make repayments on various loans coming due and, over the past few month,
the government has been drained of any remaining cash. With a major repayment
due to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IMF&lt;/span&gt; at the end of June, things were getting&amp;nbsp;desperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to get access to the funds that they had been promised, the Greek
government began backsliding on ever more of their promises. A call to halt
(and even reverse) privatizations gave way to pursuing &amp;#8220;partnerships&amp;#8221; with the
private sector to develop state assets, to partial privatization, to
privatization full-stop. Commitments to restore pensions to their previous
levels became a promise not to decrease them further. Promises to reduce sales
tax have turned into pledges not to raise it on essential items. A goal of
running balanced budgets (rather than a surplus) became a request to simply run
a smaller surplus. And any talk of a comprehensive investment plan to spur
growth has vanished. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s insistence that there were certain red lines which
they would not cross looked ever more&amp;nbsp;dubious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, at the eleventh hour, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; has
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jun/22/greece-deal-red-lines-blur-and-bend"&gt;given way&lt;/a&gt;
on their pledges to protect pensions and not to raise sales tax. They&amp;#8217;ve even
succumbed to calls for a higher budget surplus. To be honest, I&amp;#8217;m somewhat
surprised by this; I had expected that if they were going to give in on those
issues then they would have done it before now. All I can conclude is that the
leadership really didn&amp;#8217;t know what it was doing and had persisted in the blind
belief that Europe was bluffing and would give in if they waited long enough.
But to anyone with half a brain it should have been obvious that this was a
delusion, at least after the agreement in&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Left Platform, this has long been the case. Prominent members have
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/03/greece-syriza-eurogroup-negotiations-austerity/"&gt;consistently&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/04/syriza-eurozone-default-exit-stathis/"&gt;been calling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/05/kouvelakis-syriza-ecb-grexit/"&gt;for a&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/05/greece-syriza-european-union-austerity-troika/"&gt;break with&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/06/kouvelakis-greece-europe-negotiations-debt-default/"&gt;Europe&lt;/a&gt;
since February. Economist and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MP&lt;/span&gt; Costas Lapavitsas has been
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/03/lapavitsas-varoufakis-grexit-syriza/"&gt;urging an exit&lt;/a&gt;
from the Eurozone since before the election and has
&lt;a href="http://www.versobooks.com/books/1949-against-the-troika"&gt;drawn up plans&lt;/a&gt;
for how this could be accomplished. A growing number of people on the left
of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s mainstream faction have also been won over to this view after having
witnessed the ever greater concessions which have been offered in order to
avoid rupture with Europe. However, none of this has affected the official
discourse of the party and, as such, the Greek public has been fed the delusion
that relief from austerity is possible within the Euro and support for some sort
of compromise&amp;#8212;which, seeing as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; has given way on virtually all of its
initial bargaining positions while the institutions have given way on hardly any, is
impossible. The end result: Greeks remain totally unprepared for any sort of
rupture with Europe, having been scared stiff by the media and pandering
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; politicians of the consequences of doing anything which might endanger
their place in the&amp;nbsp;Euro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what now? Well, there are
&lt;a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2015/06/deal-with-greece-still-looks-wobbly.html"&gt;still questions&lt;/a&gt;
over whether a deal will actually be reached. But if it is, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s leaders
will still need to sell it to the rest of the party. And it is
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jun/23/greek-crisis-bailout-deal-eurozone-crucial-optimism-rises"&gt;not at all clear&lt;/a&gt; that this will happen. While it
may get the support of a majority of the cabinet, there is every sign that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s coalition partner will reject it (especially if it involves hikes
to sales tax) and I suspect that at least 20% of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s own MPs would vote
against it. This would be enough to make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; rely on the support of
opposition parties to pass such a bill, which would be humiliating and would
damage the party&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it remains a distinct possibility that the party&amp;#8217;s central
committee will vote down accepting any such deal. A few weeks ago there was
a vote on a motion to break with Europe, which lost 75-95. That means only 11
committee members would have to swing in order for such a proposal to win now.
Given the scope of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s retreat, such a result would seem entirely
possible. Then there is the prospect of discontent in the party grassroots.
Already the youth wing has held protests indicating that they would prefer
&lt;a href="http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/6a111b26-1583-11e5-8e6a-00144feabdc0.html#axzz3dvfKopVr"&gt;&amp;#8220;chaos to capitulation&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
So a split in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; ranks is looking increasingly&amp;nbsp;likeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, onto the point which caused me to write this article: how should the
international Left respond to these developments? For months socialist across
Europe have been expressing solidarity with Greeks and the Greek government,
while upstart parties have been advertising themselves as the
&lt;a href="http://podemos.info/"&gt;Spanish&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="http://leftunity.org/"&gt;British&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://hdpenglish.wordpress.com/"&gt;Turkish&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;. Should they continue to offer &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; their
unconditional support? Should they condemn this&amp;nbsp;retreat?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a tricky question, made all the harder by these groups&amp;#8217; uncritical approach
to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; over the past while. Billing yourself as a party in the image of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; will be distinctly damaging if &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; is forced to retreat. I think it&amp;#8217;s
fair to say that we on the Left must continue to offer the Greek people our
solidarity. However, no such solidarity should be extended to any &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; member
who is willing to implement austerity. Fair enough, they are in an incredibly
difficult situation and it is all too easy for us to criticize when we can&amp;#8217;t
even imagine being able to form a government in our home countries. But the fact
remains, if we are to be at all consistent then we must not endorse anyone who
implements austerity, whether they come from a left-wing background or&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Free Greece from the European Prison" class="img-center" src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/greeceEuropeCage.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what should &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; do? From the comfort of my armchair in a country which
has not been ravaged by austerity and is safely on its own currency and who
won&amp;#8217;t be hurt if things go wrong, here are
my thoughts. For starters, they should get rid of their
leader, Alexis Tsipras, finance minister, Yanis Varoufakis, and the inner circle
which surrounds them. This group has clearly revealed
themselves to be incapable of pushing back austerity in Greece, let alone of
laying the ground for overcoming capitalism. At the very least, Varoufakis
should be forced to&amp;nbsp;resign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes the problem that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; does not have a mandate for breaking with
Europe. As I said earlier, they were elected promising to end austerity while
remaining in the Eurozone. However, nor do they have any mandate to implement
austerity as they look prepared to do. I&amp;#8217;m not totally adverse to the concept
of pushing ahead and breaking with austerity, leaving the Euro if necessary,
mandate be damned. To be sure, such an approach has risks, but I can&amp;#8217;t help but
feel that those risks are better than the certainty of austerity-induced
misery within the Euro. 
In all probability, this will require a fresh election or a referendum in order
to justify it to the electorate. What&amp;#8217;s
more, there is a very good chance that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; would lose such an election and
it would almost certainly lose such a referendum. Well, so be&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Greek people decide that they would prefer austerity over leaving the
Euro, then &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; should resign. Let a party which really believes in austerity
be the one to implement it. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; would be better off in opposition, agitating
for an end to austerity even if it does mean a break with Europe. This would be
a serious setback but, unlike giving in to austerity, not a fatal one.
Let &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; live to fight another&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry I haven&amp;#8217;t provided any references here. It&amp;#8217;s fairly common knowledge for anyone whose been following the Greek crisis and I didn&amp;#8217;t have the energy to track the citations down when I was writing this.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it wasn&amp;#8217;t clear even before the election. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Austerity"></category><category term="Europe"></category><category term="SYRIZA"></category><category term="Socialism"></category><category term="Elections"></category></entry><entry><title>Let’s Talk About Bell</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/lets-talk-about-bell.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-28T14:15:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2015-01-28:lets-talk-about-bell.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;#8217;s that time of year again. The good people at Bell, through their
Let&amp;#8217;s Talk campaign, are once again
donating money to mental health initiatives. All they ask in return is that
we spread the word by sharing their posts about it on Facebook. Isn&amp;#8217;t that
nice of&amp;nbsp;them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Let's Talk ad" src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/bell-lets-talk.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, no, it&amp;#8217;s not, on several levels. First and foremost, if they really care
about mental health then surely they can just donate the money anyway, rather
than only do so if people share their Facebook posts. Which let&amp;#8217;s us know that
mental health is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what they really care about here. As, I suspect, with
most corporate donations, the real motivation is how it will effect their image.
Donating to charity will make them appear to be generous and good corporate
citizens, at least to those who are less cynical than me. Presumably they feel
that this will make people slightly more likely to choose them over Rogers (or
whatever other company you decide on from the myriad of&amp;#8212;pardon me, virtually
&lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;other choices that exist in&amp;nbsp;Canada).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here Bell are exceptionally clever. In addition to the usual posturing you
get when a company donates to a good cause, this campaign is all about providing
Bell with advertising. It&amp;#8217;s built into the model, as the more people who share
Bell&amp;#8217;s post, the more money they will donate.
They say that for every time their post
is shared they will donate 5 cents to mental health initiatives. According to
one website, it costs about 25 cents to reach 1000 people on Facebook. That
means that each person sharing the Bell post would only need 201 friends in
order for this to be cheaper.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is far cheaper than advertising in
conventional media, or even most other online media. Furthermore, these shared
Bell posts will not be susceptible to adblocking software, as normal Facebook
advertising&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we&amp;#8217;ve established that Bell is not doing this out of the kindness of their
heart, but because of the positive impact on their brand and the advertising
which it generates. But surely we can still be happy about the positive outcome,
regardless of the motives behind it? Well, in a sense I suppose we should, as
this money is certainly better spent on mental health initiatives than on
returns to shareholders. But then again, we shouldn&amp;#8217;t. If Bell feels that it
has this money to give away, then to me that indicates that they aren&amp;#8217;t being
taxed enough. If they were then the revenue could be used by the government to
provide mental health initiative directly. Moreover, it would be under our
democratic control to decide if this is, indeed, the best way to spend it.
Maybe we&amp;#8217;d decide that there is some other health concern which would be a
better use of the money. As it stand now, we have no choice in the&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might ask why we should have a choice. After all, it&amp;#8217;s Bell&amp;#8217;s money. But
where does Bell get it&amp;#8217;s money from? Consumers, of course. So it&amp;#8217;s all of our
money really. That means that we should have a say over how it&amp;#8217;s spent.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Furthermore, as a way of collecting money to provide services, this is highly
regressive. Why should the amount that we spend on telecom determine how much
we contribute towards mental health initiatives? Shouldn&amp;#8217;t those who have more
money be contributing a greater percentage of their income? This is the
approach we take to taxation, after all. This argument, of course,
applies to all corporate charity. Given this, surely the best way to fund things
like mental health initiatives is via&amp;nbsp;taxation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Bell, if you want to help contribute that money to good causes, why don&amp;#8217;t
you give it to the government? They can spend it as necessary. Better yet, you
could let yourself be voluntarily nationalized, so that telecom could be
provided at cost, or even for free. Let this essential service, like those
surrounding mental health, be funded&amp;nbsp;progressively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fairness, that is probably rather optimistic, as there is plenty of overlap between people&amp;#8217;s groups of friends. Nonetheless, it&amp;#8217;s pretty good value.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you feel tempted to argue that this logic applies to any way in which a company spends its money, then I agree. That is why I&amp;#8217;m a socialist and believe in public ownership.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Charity"></category><category term="Democracy"></category><category term="Accountability"></category><category term="Advertising"></category><category term="Telecom"></category></entry><entry><title>Fixing Pharmaceuticals</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/fixing-pharmaceuticals.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-28T22:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2014-06-28:fixing-pharmaceuticals.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mortar and pestle--the symbol for pharmacies in Canada." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/mortarPestle.jpg" /&gt;
Several weeks ago, now, I read a news story on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CBC&lt;/span&gt; about the
&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/drug-shortages-worsening-as-health-canada-starts-study-to-address-it-1.2652581"&gt;problem of drug shortages&lt;/a&gt;.
It appears that it is not uncommon for pharmaceutical companies (I&amp;#8217;m going to
avoid the term &amp;#8220;Big Pharma&amp;#8221; here, as to me it always sound like a juvenile
attempt at fear-mongering) to suddenly stop, or at least drastically scale down,
production of frequently used drugs. Unfortunately, no real solutions were
being offered to this. At most, Health Canada was trying to make it mandatory
for the manufacturers to report&amp;nbsp;shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is by no means the only problem that exists with pharmaceutical companies.
I vaguely remember hearing several years ago on an American news channel that
many companies were no longer producing generics, as they are not very
profitable. Of course, generics are a lot cheaper for consumers, as they are
not subject to the legal monopoly of patent law. Patents themselves are
problematic as they increase prices, but some form of patent protection seems
to be needed in order to encourage innovation and the development of new
drugs by the private&amp;nbsp;sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even patents aren&amp;#8217;t always enough to encourage the research we need. This
became clear in a recent report by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CBC&lt;/span&gt; that pharmaceutical companies
&lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/health/antibiotic-scientist-must-push-discovery-to-market-1.2686347?cmp=rss"&gt;do not seem to be interested in developing new antibiotics&lt;/a&gt;.
The reason for this is that this is quite a research-intensive process with
relatively low returns, as antibiotics aren&amp;#8217;t used that much compared to
medication for chronic conditions. However, it is absolutely vital that new
antibiotics are developed as old ones are becoming ineffective against
antibiotic-resistant&amp;nbsp;bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is becoming so acute that even
&lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/"&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;, a liberal but hardly a socialist
publication, published an editorial calling for all pharmaceutical companies
to be converted non-profit bodies charged with pursuing the public interest.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Whether this meant nationalization or simply conversion to independent
non-profit organizations (or some mixture of the two) I am not sure.
In any case,
I strongly support such a demand and think that it would be enormously
beneficial. Those who know me well won&amp;#8217;t be surprised by this, as it seems that
my response to just about any problem that I see in the economy is to
nationalize the relevant sector.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in this case I am perfectly willing to call for a more pragmatic
solution&amp;#8212;at least for the time being. Given how important a steady supply of
drugs is to the healthcare system, you don&amp;#8217;t want to do anything that could
seriously disrupt their production. Also, this is a problem which really does
need to be fixed as soon as possible and, while the nationalization of a whole
sector would never win broad support in the near future,&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; a more
moderate idea might. Not to say that this idea isn&amp;#8217;t radical given the current
political climate, but it is something which could be justified based on
pragmatism and could still seem at least vaguely conceivable to the general&amp;nbsp;public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My proposal is fairly simple: the creation of a new Crown Corporation.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Since
most people my age won&amp;#8217;t know what this is (it having been so
long since any new ones have been created) I&amp;#8217;ll explain: a Crown Corporation is
a companies which, rather than being owned by private individuals or listed
on the stock market, is owned by the government. The only significant example
in Nova Scotia is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NSLC&lt;/span&gt; (the liquor stores). In most of Canada (although not Nova
Scotia) the power companies are owned by the provincial government.
Federal Crown Corporations include Canada Post, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CBC&lt;/span&gt;, and Via Rail.
We used to own a lot more too: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NS&lt;/span&gt; Power, Air Canada, the Uranium mines,
Canadian National Railway, and  Petro-Canada, among others. However,
these were sold
off in the &amp;#8216;80s and &amp;#8216;90s, purportedly to improve the efficiency of these
companies although I&amp;#8217;m inclined to think that it was primarily for ideological&amp;nbsp;reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to my point. I think that the government should create a new Crown
Corporation which, for the sake of argument, I shall call Pharmacy Canada.
Pharmacy Canada would be charged with the development of new drugs which would
tend to have a low rate of return on investment (such as antibiotics) as well
as producing generic drugs. These would be sold at cost to the provincial health
authorities. They could also be sold slightly above cost to other developed
countries and, perhaps, at a subsidized rate to developing countries. An
additional role that could be played by Pharmacy Canada would be to act as a
bulk-purchaser of those drugs which still needed to be obtained from the
private sector. These would then be sold on, at cost, to the provinces as well.
The advantage of such centralized purchasing that it would place
Pharmacy Canada in a position to negotiate lower prices. This is a system
which has been used successfully by charities to deliver cheaper drugs to
developing countries and is, in fact, called for by the Green Party (although
no doubt they would balk at the idea of actually &lt;em&gt;producing&lt;/em&gt; drugs in the public
sector). All of these policies would help to reduce the price of drugs,
stabilizing the
fastest growing component of healthcare costs and making our public healthcare
system more&amp;nbsp;sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all eminently achievable even within the current political situation.
While it would, no doubt, be heavily lobbied against by the pharmaceutical
companies, I don&amp;#8217;t see what they could actually do to prevent it. I suppose they
could retaliate through capital flight, although I don&amp;#8217;t see how this would be
in their interest. If they were to try then their old factories could be bought
up by Pharmacy Canada, thus protecting jobs. While setting up a new Crown
Corporation would require some capital, interest rates remain low and the
federal government has a high credit rating, allowing it to borrow cheaply.
The federal deficit is almost gone and we could be running a substantial
surplus if we were to return taxes to their 2000 levels. Thus I don&amp;#8217;t think that
there is any real financial argument against establishing Pharmacy&amp;nbsp;Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary objection to this would be ideological: the belief that the
government is not capable of running a successful, productive, company. Such
attitudes are wide-spread, even among liberals and social democrats (e.g. the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt;). While there have been some issues with Crown Corporations in the past, I
still think that they were much better run than people give them credit for.
They may not have had the profit margins of private enterprise, but this is
because they were meant to be meeting social, not just purely economic
objectives. Objecting to this (as is done by my father) is to miss the entire
purpose of a Crown Corporation; if you wanted it to be run just like a private
company then you&amp;#8217;d have left it in the private sector in the first place.
Although Pharmacy Canada wouldn&amp;#8217;t deliver the same profit margins as the
existing private pharmaceutical companies, it would be able to perform
functions which they are
failing to do. This sort of value can not be reflected in simple calculations
of&amp;nbsp;efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I suspect that the traditional means of running Crown Corporations&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; would be able to achieve much of what I describe, I believe that
even greater accomplishments could be made if Pharmacy Canada were to be run
along socialist lines. This would mean that the board would consist of
representatives of researchers, doctors, employees, patients, and government.
The advantages to this are twofold. First,
and more abstractly, it would ensure that the company was run democratically,
something which I think has value in its own right. But second, the
representation of researchers and doctors would ensure that fruitful avenues of
research were being pursued. My strong suspicion is that this would prove a
mores successful (as measured in health outcomes, rather than profit) way of
directing research than what is currently provided by the private&amp;nbsp;sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, being the realist/cynic that I am, I realize that the creation of Pharmacy
Canada stands absolutely no chance of happening even if the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt; were elected
in 2015. The idea of public enterprise has simply crept too far outside of the
political mainstream. But this is no reason to stop talking about it; if it is
ever to get back into the political mainstream then it is something which must
become broadly popular and also seriously discussed in progressive political
circles. We need organizations like &lt;a href="https://www.broadbentinstitute.ca/en"&gt;The Broadbent Institute&lt;/a&gt;,
the &lt;a href="http://www.canadians.org/"&gt;Council of Canadians&lt;/a&gt;, and the
&lt;a href="https://www.policyalternatives.ca/"&gt;Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives&lt;/a&gt;
not only to call for such a policy but to perform studies detailing how to do
it. Nor should we be afraid to suggest it as individuals. Because, at least in
this case, the radical is becoming the&amp;nbsp;pragmatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this article would now be archived and only accessible to those with a subscription, so I can&amp;#8217;t post a link.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do realize that this alone won&amp;#8217;t fix all of the problems, as democratic control is needed over public enterprise if it is to truly behave differently than private enterprise (other than just behaving slightly more bureaucratically). Nonetheless, nationalization is usually a good start in my view, as it begins to address the questions of ownership, control, and power.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a few countries, there are a few sectors which may prove an exception to this. For example, the rail and energy sectors in Britain or the financial sector in Greece.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who are unaware, in Canada &amp;#8220;the Crown&amp;#8221; tends to refer to &amp;#8220;the state&amp;#8221;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boards of directors were appointed by Parliament, consisting mainly of businessmen (and I use the gendered term deliberately) and former politicians.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Pharmaceuticals"></category><category term="Antibiotics"></category><category term="Crown Corporations"></category><category term="Socialism"></category></entry><entry><title>On Europe, the Left, and the Future</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/on-europe-the-left-and-the-future.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-23T23:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2014-05-23:on-europe-the-left-and-the-future.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who weren&amp;#8217;t aware (and, frankly, I suspect that will be all of
you), there are currently elections going on for the European Parliament. This
is, in principle, the legislative body of the European Union, although in
practice it is debatable how much power it actually holds. For this reason,
European elections don&amp;#8217;t usually attract too much attention, even in Europe,
and tend to have turnouts similar to those in municipal&amp;nbsp;elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alex Tsipras campaigning for the Party of the European Left." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/euroLeft.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as an international observer, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; quite interesting about
the European Parliament (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;) is the shear diversity of parties represented in
it. Compared to the recent Nova Scotian election, where there was so much
homogeneity that you would be
hard-pressed to tell which party anyone belonged to, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt; elections overwhelm
you with choice. But, before I go into what the various choices are, I&amp;#8217;ll just
provide a bit of background on how the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every country is given a certain number of seats in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;, distributed
according to population.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Exactly how Members of the European Parliament
(MEPs) are elected is left up to the individual countries, the only
requirement being that some form of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proportional_representation"&gt;proportional representation&lt;/a&gt;
is used. In each country, the various national parties will put forward
candidates, some of whom will be elected. Most of the national parties will
also hold an affiliation to a European party. Elected MEPs sit in groups with
their national party, which in turn sits in a group with similar parties from
other countries, roughly along the lines of the various European parties.
Because these groups consist of a collection of national parties, they won&amp;#8217;t
necessarily have a single, coherent position&amp;#8212;a national party will often vote
differently from its group. Additionally, the Europarties play little roll
outside of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;; national parties campaign individually on their own set
of policies. Of
course, this all seems unnecessarily complicated and confusing, but there you
are. As best as I can tell, the reason for this complexity is that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;
never really arose out of a plan but was more stitched together bit by&amp;nbsp;bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The groups within the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt; are (with the main Europarty composing them given
in parentheses, if more than&amp;nbsp;one):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European People&amp;#8217;s Party&lt;/strong&gt;: Pro-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; (support tighter integration),
conservative. Angela Merkel&amp;#8217;s Christian Democrats are notable&amp;nbsp;members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats&lt;/strong&gt;: Pro-Europe, social
democracy (centre-left). While consisting of the Party of European Socialists,
in reality
they are not that different from the European People&amp;#8217;s Party when it comes to&amp;nbsp;economics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alliance of Liberals and Democrats for Europe Group&lt;/strong&gt;: Pro-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;, centrist,
socially liberal, free-market&amp;nbsp;economics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Greens&amp;#8212;European Free Alliance&lt;/strong&gt; (European Green Party): Green politics,
and representatives of nations without states (ex: Scotland, Wales, Catalonia).
Economically progressive in principle, but been known to give in to&amp;nbsp;conservatism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Conservatives and Reformists&lt;/strong&gt; (Movement for European Reform):
Conservative, anti-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. The British Conservatives are part of this party, but not
many other&amp;nbsp;members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European United Left&amp;#8212;Nordic Green Left&lt;/strong&gt; (Party of the European Left):
Socialists and communists. Supportive of European integration but don&amp;#8217;t like
the current setup of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Europe of Freedom and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt; (Movement for a Europe of Liberties and
Democracy): Anti-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;, highly conservative, right-wing populist. Tend to be very
anti-immigrant and, in particular, anti-Muslim. Similarities to the Tea&amp;nbsp;Party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list is given in descending order of the size of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt; groups. What is
interesting about this election, in particular, is that the more radical parties
are expected to do well; the European Left and Europe of Freedom
and Democracy are both hoping to make gains.
The latter has proven especially good at
tapping into discontent and anti-politics sentiment, often presenting themselves
as a real alternative to the now indistinguishable main-stream parties. I
suppose this is, strictly speaking, true as the main-stream parties tend to be
pro-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and in agreement over centre-right economics. However, it is disingenuous
in the extreme for them to portray themselves as representing ordinary people;
for example, one of the most notable constituent national parties, the United
Kingdom Independence Party (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UKIP&lt;/span&gt;), is led by wealthy financier and
arch-&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Farage"&gt;Thatcherite&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Farage"&gt;Nigel Farage&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, since he drinks,
smokes, and is more plain-speaking than leaders of the larger parties, he
somehow comes off as a man of the people. This has, at times, bizarre results.
For example, a
&lt;a href="http://yougov.co.uk/news/2013/11/04/nationalise-energy-and-rail-companies-say-public/"&gt;poll showed&lt;/a&gt;
that an overwhelming majority of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UKIP&lt;/span&gt; voters support
renationalization of rail and energy companies. The only party whose voters
supported these policies in higher numbers was Labour (unsurprising, given its
socialist origins). Yet &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UKIP&lt;/span&gt; has a radical &amp;#8220;small government&amp;#8221; policy, more
extreme even than the Conservatives&amp;#8217;.&lt;sup id="fnref:1.5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1.5" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All in all, it seems
that it is social policy that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UKIP&lt;/span&gt; and  Europe of Freedom and Democracy attract
people with. Sad to say, many working class people with progressive economics
are distinctly&amp;nbsp;xenophobic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far more encouraging is the growth of the European United Left&amp;#8212;Nordic Green
Left (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EUL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt;). The national parties in this group are, to a greater or lesser
degree,
socialists. They are all vehemently opposed to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoliberalism"&gt;neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and most are (at least officially) opposed to
capitalism itself. Policies vary from stronger regulation and increased public
spending, to (re)nationalisation of banks and energy companies
(which seems to be
the standard position of group members), to outright revolutionary (although not
necessarily insurrectionary&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) socialism. Additionally, they call for making
the structures of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; much more democratic. As you might have gathered, the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; is a rather ungainly institution. There are three governing bodies, only one
of which (the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;) is directly elected. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EUL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt; supports giving more power to the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt; in order to help remedy this. In addition, the European Central Bank (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECB&lt;/span&gt;, in
charge of the Euro&amp;#8217;s monetary policy) is not under any sort of democratic
control. This, in particular, is something that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EUL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt; wishes to change, with
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt; appointing the Banks governors and setting its mandate (as is done with
most central banks, including the Bank of Canada). They have good reason for
this, as the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ECB&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s current policies have exacerbated the crises in Italy,
Greece, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;#8220;the periphery&amp;#8221;). It is resolving these crises that
makes up the centrepiece of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EUL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt; policies. The intention is to implement an industrial and redistributive
policy which will eliminate the imbalances between &amp;#8220;the centre&amp;#8221; (Germany,
France, etc.) and the periphery. While these proposals are really social
democratic, rather than anti-capitalist, they would nonetheless be of great
help and would likely make it easier for national governments to implement more radical&amp;nbsp;policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is some debate over how committed to European integration the
Left should be. Some feel that, because neoliberalism has more or less been
written into the very structure of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;, the Left should be Eurosceptical.
However, as described above, the general position is that the Left should
reform the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. There appear to be two main reasons to pursue this policy. One
is an objection to nationalism, which caused so much carnage in the first half
of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century. It was to prevent something like this from ever
happening again that European integration was originally begun. The second
reason is that it is felt you would need to be coming to power on a continental
scale if you seriously want to confront, let alone do away with, capitalism.
Otherwise any country attempting the transition to socialism would end up
isolated as capitalist nations began committing economic warfare (as happened
to Chile in the late&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8216;60s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of the above arguments are strong. However, the issues arises of what will
happen if a Left government comes to power in one country much sooner than the
others. This is not just idle speculation, as there is a very good chance that
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EUL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt; member &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriza"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; will come to
power in Greece in their next election.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; has campaigned around ending
the austerity in Greece, which is causing massive damage to their economy and
creating a humanitarian crisis. However, doing so would involve renegotiating
bailout terms with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. But, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; is also determined to stay in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;
and to keep Greece on the Euro. It is unclear that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; would allow them to
do both of these things. Undoubtedly, it would be difficult for Greece to leave
the Euro and it would also be extremely unpopular for them to pull out of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. From my knowledge, it appears that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; will only go as far as the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;
lets them. Hopefully, this will be far enough to resolve the Greek crisis
(kicking out Greece would likely be damaging to Europe as well), but that might
not be the case. For what it&amp;#8217;s worth, my personal view is that Greece
shouldn&amp;#8217;t pull out on its own but if, in the course of implementing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s
policies, they get kicked out then so be&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting case study (if only because all of the debates here are in
English) is the formation of the new &lt;a href="http://leftunity.org/"&gt;Left Unity&lt;/a&gt; party
in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;. This party is actually fairly radical compared to some of its
Continental counterparts, calling for a much greater degree of nationalization
(although I suppose that Britain has a history of more extensive public
ownership than most countries, so perhaps that isn&amp;#8217;t surprising). The issue here
is that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; regulations would make it vary difficult for Left Unity to implement
many of its policies if elected. However, the reasons for staying in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;
that I mentioned above are just as true for Britain as anywhere else and, as
a result, Left Unity has much the same set of policies regarding the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;. In this
case, I think the answer is much more clean-cut. The radical left in
Britain is lagging far behind the rest of Europe,&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so it is unlikely that
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; would have a Left government before the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; as a whole. Therefore, they
might as well advocate staying in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt; and take the same position as the rest of the
European&amp;nbsp;Left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I think that, with the possible exception of countries like Greece, the
Left should be trying the achieve socialism at the European level. Various
think-tanks, such the &lt;a href="http://www.rosalux.de/english/foundation.html"&gt;Rosa-Luxemburg Siftung&lt;/a&gt; (associated with the German party &lt;a href="http://en.die-linke.de/die-linke/welcome/"&gt;Die Linke&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="http://transform-network.net/home.html"&gt;transform!&lt;/a&gt;
(loosely associated with the &lt;a href="http://www.european-left.org/"&gt;Party of the European Left&lt;/a&gt;) have called for the ultimate establishment of the United Socialist
States of Europe. This, I think, is an admirable goal. However, I am not
convinced that this goal can be achieved with the current European leftist
institutions. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UEL&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NGL&lt;/span&gt; and the Party of the European Left are both much too
loose as associations. To the extent that they coordinate trans-European
campaigns
at all, they tend to be centred around policies making up the least radical
common denominator of their members. For the most part, as with all of the
Europarties, active campaigning is left to the individual national members.
However, as is generally acknowledged, building socialism requires a Europe-wide
movement. That means a truly Europe-wide&amp;nbsp;party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I feel, to be successful, the members of the Party of the European
Left will have to give up their individual identities. They&amp;#8217;ll have to become
national chapters of a continent-wide party. And, do you know what? I&amp;#8217;m actually
somewhat hopeful. For all the mess that the world is in and all the ways that
mess is likely to get worse, I can&amp;#8217;t help but feel that we&amp;#8217;ll pull through it.
It won&amp;#8217;t be easy, but the worthwhile things seldom are. To the extent that I
have faith in anything, I have faith that humanity is capable of being better
than it is today. I think Europe can do it&amp;#8212;it can overcome the more
unpleasant parts of human nature and build a society based on cooperation and
solidarity. And if Europe can do it, then so can others. Maybe one day, before
I die, I&amp;#8217;ll wake up in a socialist &lt;a href="http://www.socialisthistory.ca/Docs/CCF/ReginaManifesto.htm"&gt;Cooperative Commonwealth of Canada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, much like the distribution of MPs between provinces in Canada, smaller countries are favoured, possessing more seats per capita than larger countries.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1.5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UKIP&lt;/span&gt; wants to replace the public health-care system with vouchers for private hospitals.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1.5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policies of privatization, deregulation, budget cuts, decreased taxes (especially in the upper tax brackets), free trade, etc.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many left-wing thinkers nowadays argue that revolution doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily mean insurrection&amp;#8212;it might simply refer to a period of rapid, fundamental change in society.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Right tends to become hysterical at this prospect, on the Left it is currently very fashionable to criticize &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; for moving to the right. Personally, I&amp;#8217;m not convinced that they&amp;#8217;ve actually moved anywhere and think that any perception that they have is simply revealing what was always present in their ideology. For a good discussion of these issues, I recommend this lecture: &lt;a href="http://socialistproject.ca/leftstreamed/ls215.php"&gt;Syriza and the European Elections&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this are complicated, but they seem to include the fact that Britain lacks proportional representation and that the British Left is so notoriously fractious. It&amp;#8217;s pretty bad when the Wikipedia&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_British_political_parties#Minor_far-left_parties"&gt;list of British political parties&lt;/a&gt; needs a whole section just for the Far-Left. &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Europe"></category><category term="Socialism"></category><category term="Party of the European Left"></category><category term="Elections"></category><category term="SYRIZA"></category><category term="Left Unity"></category></entry><entry><title>On Socialists and Scotsmen</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/on-socialists-and-scotsmen.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-28T01:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-12-28:on-socialists-and-scotsmen.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Us socialists are often accused of preaching a failed ideology; one which has
been shown to inevitably result in totalitarianism and impoverishment. To this
most socialists will respond in one of two ways. Some (mostly those from the 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comintern"&gt;Third International&lt;/a&gt;, 
but also a few  radical elements of the 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist_International"&gt;Second International&lt;/a&gt;) 
act as apologists for the old Eastern European regimes (and possibly those in
Asia as well, although the 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sino-Soviet_split"&gt;Sino-Soviet&lt;/a&gt; split complicates
matters there). Others, such as myself, respond by saying that we don&amp;#8217;t see how
socialism can have failed when the world has yet to see a socialist society. This
tends to be the view of Trotskyist (such as those in one the various iterations
of the 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_International_(disambiguation)"&gt;Fourth International&lt;/a&gt;), 
libertarian socialists, and the more ideologically self-consistent democratic 
socialists. An example of such an argument is provided in the video&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315"  style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/K4Tq4VE8eHQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inevitable objection that is given, not only by the right but also by the
centre-left, is that this is an example of the &amp;#8220;No True Scotsman Fallacy.&amp;#8221;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_true_Scotsman"&gt;Wikipedia describes this&lt;/a&gt; like&amp;nbsp;so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No true Scotsman is an informal fallacy, an ad hoc attempt to retain an 
unreasoned assertion. When faced with a counterexample to a universal claim 
(&amp;#8220;no Scotsman would do such a thing&amp;#8221;), rather than denying the counterexample 
or rejecting the original universal claim, this fallacy modifies the subject of 
the assertion to exclude the specific case or others like it by rhetoric, 
without reference to any specific objective rule (&amp;#8220;no true Scotsman would do 
such a&amp;nbsp;thing&amp;#8221;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, supposedly, it is logically invalid to explain away any unpleasantness
by dismissing the regime responsible as not really socialist. Doing so is to
dismiss counterarguments without actually addressing it. However, here I feel
that there is a misunderstanding of my point. These people misunderstand my 
argument to be &amp;#8220;socialist societies will
inevitably be democratic ones.&amp;#8221; However, for me, such a statement would be a
tautology: what I mean when I speak of socialism is &amp;#8220;collective ownership of and
&lt;em&gt;democratic control&lt;/em&gt; over the economy.&amp;#8221; For me 
(&lt;a href="http://socialistparty-usa.net/principles.html"&gt;and others&lt;/a&gt;), democracy is part 
of the definition of socialism. Any regime that claims to be socialistic but is a 
dictatorship (I&amp;#8217;m looking at you, Cuba) is lying, at least by my definition
of socialism. True, such a regime might claim to be socialism, but that doesn&amp;#8217;t
make it so; just because East Germany was called the German Democratic Republic
didn&amp;#8217;t make it a democracy, after&amp;nbsp;all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, some will claim that socialism will never be implemented democratically
because people won&amp;#8217;t want it. Thus, socialism will inevitably have to be
imposed using violence and oppression. The first part of this argument is a
perfectly valid position to take, although not one that I think is true 
(actually, there is some historical evidence to the contrary, so anyone making
this argument will have to be very careful not to end up using  the &amp;#8220;No True 
Scotsman Fallacy&amp;#8221; themselves). However, in my view, the second part of this
argument is meaninglessness. If it is being imposed by a dictatorship then
it can not be socialism. Effectively what is being said, then, is that 
socialism is impossible. This is also a perfectly valid position, but I
don&amp;#8217;t think that there is clear evidence one way or the other with regards
to this&amp;nbsp;question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, horrible things have been done &lt;em&gt;in the name of&lt;/em&gt;
socialism, and even quite recently the likes of Hugo Chavez have done some rather
slimy things in the name of socialism. This potential is something which socialists
must constantly be vigilant of. We must accept the ugly parts of our movement&amp;#8217;s
history (and, for that matter, its present). Failure to do so is not only
dishonest, but dangerous. However, these dangers do not discredit socialism 
itself, but rather some (and, thankfully, an ever decreasing number) of the
social&lt;em&gt;ists&lt;/em&gt;. What&amp;#8217;s more, I honestly believe that any risk of totalitarianism
posed by campaigning for democratic socialism is far smaller than the risks
that humanity face under&amp;nbsp;capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for claims that socialism results in poverty: we have no data, seeing
as there have been no socialist economies (at least, not that have lasted 
for any significant amount of time before being crushed by external forces).
I don&amp;#8217;t think that this will necessarily be the case, but that&amp;#8217;s only a guess.
There&amp;#8217;s no doubt that there were serious problems with the Warsaw Pact
economies. We have to seriously consider whether centralized planning can
ever be made to work (personally, I think that it would be undesirable even
if it could be done). Certainly, the planning techniques used by the Soviet Union
have been discredited. But I hope, and honestly believe, that in a technological, 
democratic society some form of 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decentralized_planning_(economics)"&gt;decentralized economic planning&lt;/a&gt; 
will be possible. Even if not, there are ideas such as cooperative ownership
in a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_socialism"&gt;market socialist&lt;/a&gt; economy,
which seem to me to be eminently feasible, if&amp;nbsp;unambitious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, no, I am not committing the &amp;#8220;No True Scotsman Fallacy&amp;#8221; when I say that the
so-called communist countries were not, in fact, socialist. It is not a 
contradiction for me to
be a socialist and yet to oppose Soviet-style communism. It just so happens that
there are multiple definitions of socialism and the definition which applies to
me (and many others) is directly opposed to that used by the Soviet Union and
its&amp;nbsp;supporters.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Socialism"></category><category term="No True Scotsmen Fallacy"></category><category term="Noam Chomsky"></category><category term="Democracy"></category></entry><entry><title>Denouncing the Dumb Diatribe on the Discontinuation of Door-to-Door Delivery</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/denouncing-the-dumb-diatribe-on-the-discontinuation-of-door-to-door-delivery.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-12-23:denouncing-the-dumb-diatribe-on-the-discontinuation-of-door-to-door-delivery.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you may know, Canada Post &lt;a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/ottawa/canada-post-to-phase-out-urban-home-mail-delivery-1.2459618"&gt;recently announced&lt;/a&gt;
that they will be making some changes. Two in particular are of note: a price 
increase on stamps and the phasing out of door-to-door delivery in urban 
areas. The latter measure will allow the elimination of about 8000 jobs. 
However, thanks to the strength of the postal workers&amp;#8217; union, no one will 
actually be fired; rather, the workforce reductions will be achieved by&amp;nbsp;attrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Community mailboxes, of the sort I've grown up with." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/mailboxes.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predictably, the left has had a conniption over all of this. A typical example
can be &lt;a href="http://rabble.ca/blogs/bloggers/views-expressed/2013/12/canada-post-not-on-life-support-it-being-murdered"&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;. 
In particular, they have denounced the elimination of door-to-door delivery. 
Given my politics, you may be expecting a similar reaction here. But there 
you would be 
wrong. Many parts of Canada already use the community mailboxes which will 
become the norm over the next few years. It so happens that I grew up in one 
such area. It was a daily routine to either walk and get the mail or to swing 
by the mailbox when we were driving somewhere. In the case of the latter, the 
community mailbox arrangement took at most an extra two minutes out of our 
day. In the case of the former, it forced us to get a bit of fresh air and 
exercise. Contrary to what many claim, the scheme is not particularly 
inconvenient* and certainly is not going to cause the destruction of Canada&amp;nbsp;Post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, if anything the opposite is true. Sometimes people will talk about 
ending Canada Post&amp;#8217;s monopoly and introducing competition into mail 
delivery. I
tend to be suspicious of such proposals, but if the proper regulations
were in place then I find it hard to actually justify the government monopoly 
on door-to-door daily mail delivery. Community mail boxes, however, make this
much more difficult in my opinion. Do we really want to allow every upstart
mail-delivery company to have the keys to everyone&amp;#8217;s mailboxes? I think that
would be rather hard to justify (especially given that the mailboxes are
government property) and could thus potentially reinforce Canada
Post&amp;#8217;s monopoly status. It obviously would be no protection against 
privatization, but in the current political climate I don&amp;#8217;t know what can&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the far more concerning element of the reforms is the increase in the
price of postage. Again, I doubt that this will spell the end of a public post
office, but it is nonetheless a significant increase. Prices will be going up
by 22 cents when buying stamps in packs and by 37 cents when buying
individually (although most people protesting the changes are only 
bothering to
mention the higher of these two figures). Given that Canada Post&amp;#8217;s delivery
times are, let&amp;#8217;s face it, less than impressive, cheapness is one of the few 
things it has going for it. It perplexes me that the prices increases seem to
be of secondary concern to those on the&amp;nbsp;left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind you, this whole thing perplexes me to some extent. As I mentioned 
earlier, community mailboxes are not exactly new; large parts of Canada have
been using them for years. If they are such a terrible idea, why the hell are
we only hearing it now? Are the people who intend to protest the post office
changes going to push for the elimination of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; community mailboxes and the
restoration of universal door-to-door delivery? Somehow I doubt it. And which
of the other cost-saving proposals would they endorse? Reducing delivery to
three days a week seems like a much worse option to me. As does closing post
offices, which are a fantastically valuable piece of 
infrastructure which have 
the potential to perform many useful functions. I don&amp;#8217;t much like the idea
of wage reductions or restraint and, in any case, that would be difficult
given the strength of the postal union (although knowing Harper he might just
legislate it through). Prices increases certainly aren&amp;#8217;t ideal, 
as I&amp;#8217;ve already
said. Community mailboxes seem like a pretty reasonable solution, given&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it ideal? Not really. There&amp;#8217;s no denying that door-to-door delivery 
is more 
convenient. And, even if the job reductions are done by attrition, I&amp;#8217;m not 
thrilled with a reduction in the size of the public sector. It&amp;#8217;s yet another
reduction in the role played in the economy by Crown corporations, further
removing from people&amp;#8217;s consciousness the idea of public enterprise performing
a useful function. (Particularly disturbing is that the government has
appointed a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; of Canada Post who came from a company that operates
privatized post offices.) What&amp;#8217;s more, 
there are alternatives to the reduction in
service, other sources of revenue which Canada Post could pursue. Post offices
could take over some of the functions of Service Canada, for example. It would
be far more convenient for people, considering there are many more 
post offices than Service Canada&amp;nbsp;bureaus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But far more interesting is the potential for
Canada Post to offer banking services, as described in 
&lt;a href="http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2013/12/20/postal_savings_bank_could_save_mail_delivery_walkom.html"&gt;this Toronto Star article&lt;/a&gt;. 
This isn&amp;#8217;t nearly as strange an idea as it seems, as postal banks are
common in Europe and other parts of the world. 
In fact, Britain&amp;#8217;s old Gyro Bank&amp;#8212;the name of their postal bank&amp;#8212;
was (prior to its privatization in the &amp;#8216;80s) possibly the single most 
successful example of public enterprise, introducing many innovations and 
scaring the private banking sector into shaping up its act.
A similar scheme in
Canada would be an excellent idea even on its own merit. It could likely
offer Canadians superior levels of service (certainly many more branches) than
existing banks currently provide and could be used to invest in 
socially useful projects.
What&amp;#8217;s more, it would almost certainly provide Canada Post with 
enough revenue 
to make the current service reductions unnecessary. Perhaps it would be enough
to pay for universal door-to-door delivery (although I honestly have no idea 
about&amp;nbsp;that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&amp;#8217;s no doubt that there are alternatives to the service reductions at
Canada Post. Ones that would promote socialist ideals such as 
public ownership. But I honestly don&amp;#8217;t see these service reductions as 
leading to the destruction or privatization of Canada Post. They will, at 
worst, be a minor inconvenience for Canadians. Let&amp;#8217;s try to keep things in&amp;nbsp;perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*I should note here that the changes will more troublesome for seniors. 
Perhaps there could be a compromise made where you get door-to-door delivery
if you are over a certain age? But in any case, most seniors who live in 
their own houses are fairly&amp;nbsp;spry.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Canada Post"></category><category term="Crown Corporations"></category><category term="Door-to-Door Mail"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Social Democracy Was Great and Why It Isn’t the Answer</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/why-social-democracy-was-great-and-why-it-isnt-the-answer.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-13T23:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-07-13:why-social-democracy-was-great-and-why-it-isnt-the-answer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I happened to read two very interesting articles, which at first 
glance would appear to be entirely unrelated. One was in &lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21929254.600-the-wonder-year-why-1978-was-the-best-year-ever.html#.UeCPGt9hLCc"&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
magazine and explained that, although &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt; has risen fairly steadily in the west for the past several decades, the Genuine Progress Indicator (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPI&lt;/span&gt;) has slowly 
been declining since 1978. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPI&lt;/span&gt; essentially tries to
adjust the value of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt; to account for social and environmental problems (such 
as inequality and pollution). The other article was an opinion
piece in &lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2013/jun/25/europe-leaders-not-turning-austerity"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by two Canadian academics and activists
that I am rather fond of: Leo Panitch and Sam Gindin. Here they explained why 
we can&amp;#8217;t expect any attempt at a second New Deal in Europe as a way of 
combating the economic crisis: in short, without a
threat of something more radical (ie: all-out socialism), the ruling classes see
no need to engage in progressive economic&amp;nbsp;policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Graphs show that GDP has been consistently rising since 1950, while GPI has 
been in decline since the late 1970s." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/gpiPlots.jpg" /&gt;
This set of graphs, taken from &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8216;s website, shows that global &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt;
and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPI&lt;/span&gt; rose fairly steadily from 1950 to the late 1970s. 
This corresponds with the period in which Keynesianism ruled. This usually
took the form of social democracy: public ownership of key industries, strong 
trade unions, lots of regulation, a large welfare state, etc. As Panitch and
Gindin explain, the reason that this could be implemented was because there
were powerful working-class forces at work which could have led to the outright
abolition of capitalism. Faced with the prospect of losing everything, the upper
classes were willing to sacrifice a little wealth and power in order to pacify
the lower classes. This also was reflected in American foreign policy: the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt;
established the Marshall Plan in Europe to ensure that capitalism survived 
there, thus helping to ensure its survival in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the above plot, these policies were quite successful at 
ensuring increased quality of life for all. However, the welfare state was 
always dependent on the success in the private sector for revenue (with a few
exceptions, nationalised industries were not used as major revenue sources). 
Thus social democracy has always been dependent on continued capital 
accumulation. And this was its fundamental weakness. When the global slump
came in the 1970s (in Britain it was so severe that you see a large decrease
in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPI&lt;/span&gt; around 1975) it began to put the welfare state in jeopardy. In some 
countries there were attempts to break away from the dependence on private
capital accumulation (the Meidner Plan in Sweden and Mitterrand&amp;#8217;s 
nationalisation of banks in France) but the working class was not strong enough
to bring these attempts to a successful conclusion. In all countries it 
eventually proved necessary
to start scaling back the welfare state and, to one degree or another, abandon
Keynesian policies in favour of Monetarist ones. This new economic orthodoxy is
usually referred to as&amp;nbsp;neoliberalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain this took the form of Margaret Thatcher. In the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; it was Ronald
Reagan. In Canada it was Brian Mulroney. All of them implemented policies which
were harmful to the average citizen. Trade unions were weakened and could no
longer act as a force against income inequality. Industries previously devoted
to the public good were privatised and used to enrich a select few. Cuts to 
social spending hurt the poor by making once universal services available only
to those that could pay. Deregulation made it easier for companies to pollute
the environment and the emphasis on private profit meant that environmental
costs were ignored. The reasons for declining &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPI&lt;/span&gt; are clear. What is less clear
is what to do about&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panitch and Gindin show that today we lack the popular forces which made 
social democracy viable in the post-war period. There are no significant 
examples of non-capitalist states and few radical trade unions. In the minds of
most people there is no alternative to capitalism. Anti-capitalist parties are 
small and marginal (with a few exceptions, such as in Greece and, to a lesser 
extent, Spain and Portugal). The business class need not
fear the imposition of socialism; they know that the working class is currently
too disorganized to be a serious threat and thus see no need to pursue a policy
of&amp;nbsp;appeasement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this situation will very likely change in the coming years and 
decades, but there are a few questions we should address as we work to create 
new working-class institutions. One is what these movements should demand. 
Many progressive economists talk about things like reregulating the banks and 
implementing a Tobin tax. However, as
explained above, we are unlikely to be able to impose these reformist measures
without the threat of something far more radical. And, knowing what happened the
last time the left settled for reforming capitalism rather than abolishing it, 
we should not be content merely to use socialism as a threat. This time we must
&lt;em&gt;implement&lt;/em&gt; it.
Social democracy died in the 1980s and there is no point in trying to bring back
the dead. Rosa Luxemburg&amp;#8217;s sentiments are more true now than ever: 
&amp;#8220;Bourgeois society stands at the crossroads, either transition to Socialism or regression into&amp;nbsp;Barbarism.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="GDP"></category><category term="Social Democracy"></category><category term="Leo Panitch"></category><category term="Sam Gindin"></category><category term="British Politics"></category><category term="Neoliberalism"></category><category term="Socialism"></category></entry><entry><title>Was There No Alternative?</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/was-there-no-alternative.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-09T10:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-07-09:was-there-no-alternative.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made the mistake today of voicing my distinctly anti-Thatcher views. For those
of you who don&amp;#8217;t know, Margaret Thatcher was Prime Minister in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; during
the &amp;#8216;80s and oversaw the implementation of neoliberalism. She succeeded in 
crushing the trade unions, scaling back the welfare state, deregulating the
financial sector, deindustrialising Britain, and privatising a substantial
portion of public assets (including utilities, airlines, buses, coal mines,
steel manufacturing, and aerospace, among other things). These policies saw a 
massive increase in income inequality and unemployment and are often referred
to as &amp;#8220;class warfare from above.&amp;#8221; Anyway, I received a 
(fairly typical) response that Thatcher saved Britain for anarchy and bankruptcy
and that while her policies were unpleasant at the time, they were 
necessary. There are even plenty of people
on the centre-left who say things like this. It irritates me to no end, but I 
figured that it was best to avoid getting dragged into a political debate in 
public. Of course, this being me, it continued to bother me through the day, so
I&amp;#8217;ve written some of my thoughts on the matter&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to be fair, Britain&amp;#8217;s economy was a mess before she came in. It was also a 
mess for quite awhile after she came in. In fact, initially she made things 
worse. When the recovery did come it was on the back of the finance &amp;#8220;industry,&amp;#8221;
and we all know how that turned out&amp;#8230; However, there is no denying that the
British economy was in need of major restructuring. Maggie famously justified
her policies by saying that &amp;#8220;There is no alternative.&amp;#8221; This is often referred to
as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TINA&lt;/span&gt; and this is what the Thatcher-apologists have unwittingly bought into. 
And, in a sense, they aren&amp;#8217;t wrong. There was no alternative&amp;#8212;if we insisted on
maintaining&amp;nbsp;capitalism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, at about the same time that the Thatcherites came to
power we also saw the rise of the Bennites. They were a left-wing movement 
within the Labour Party, centred around the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MP&lt;/span&gt; Tony Benn. They advocated 
nationalising the financial institutions
and much of large industry. These new public enterprises were to be administered
by the workers. They felt that these measures, combined with a degree of
industrial planning (which would, if I recall, have seen a substantial retooling
of factories) and import substitution would help to restart Britain&amp;#8217;s
economy. Actually, the Labour Party was elected in the 1970s on a watered-down
version of this platform. However, they did not have the guts to pursue it and
instead implemented an early, watered-down version of Thatcherism. This prompted
a massive strike-wave, referred to as The Winter of Discontent (the 
anarchy to which Thatcher apologists refer). The irony is that the Labour 
Party brought it upon themselves. There were alternatives proposed. At least one
was even put forward the Cabinet by Tony Benn, but was viewed as too&amp;nbsp;radical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you can not justify what Margaret Thatcher did by saying that it was what 
was necessary in order to get Britain back on track. There were other options
available which were never tried. What was true, however, was that the post-War
class-compromise (the Keynesian mixed-economy) had outlive its usefulness. As 
the &amp;#8216;80s dawned, class struggle was destined to begin anew. 
The likes of Tony Benn tried, 
and very nearly succeeded, at leading the working class to victory. 
However, Mrs. Thatcher was more successful with her ruling-class offensive.
When you apologise for Thatcher, this class warfare from above is what you are 
justifying. I suspect, or at least hope, that
fewer people would be willing to defend her if they thought of it that&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PS&lt;/span&gt;: I have a certain fondness for all of the protests songs written about
Margaret Thatcher. Here are a few of my&amp;nbsp;favourites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/9t4-zDem1Sk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/IlkXQm7tSCY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/B1NyWbhCxZE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/OeuLTEXazJs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="Margaret Thatcher"></category><category term="British Politics"></category><category term="UK"></category><category term="TINA"></category><category term="Tony Benn"></category><category term="Socialism"></category></entry></feed>