<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Political Physicist</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://politicalphysicist.github.io/</id><updated>2013-08-16T20:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Science for Socialists: Introduction</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/science-for-socialists-introduction.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-16T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-08-16:science-for-socialists-introduction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you may know, my background is in the physical sciences. Well, I&amp;#8217;m 
doing my undergrad in astrophysics, at any rate. As you may also 
know, my politics essentially correspond to socialism. And by socialism,
I mean the &amp;#8220;common ownership of the means of production&amp;#8221; type, not 
just the &amp;#8220;let&amp;#8217;s maybe actually try funding our healthcare system 
properly&amp;#8221; type. So 
something I find quite upsetting is when I see these two interests coming
into conflict. To be clear, I don&amp;#8217;t think that there is anything that 
science is saying which would imply that socialism is impossible or
undesirable. Rather, the problem lies with the socialists: while much
better than the lunatic fringe of conservatives who actively oppose
science and rationalism, many socialists are nonetheless rather selective
in their use of these&amp;nbsp;tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While those on the Right will get things totally wrong with regards to
evolution and climate change (among other, smaller, things), those on the
Left have been known to say downright crazy things about nuclear power
and genetically modified organisms (among other, similar, things). The
good news is that, I hope, often when leftists get science wrong it is
more to do with ignorance/laziness than outright hostility. This means
that socialists can be set right. Or so I dare to dream. In reality, even
if any socialists read this, I imagine most of them will laugh me off as
an oddity. Nonetheless, I feel this task is important and I am probably
one of the relatively few people who actually has &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; sort of 
qualification to actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; it, in that I can speak as someone with a
decent scientific background, plenty of experience in critical thinking,
and a political orientation that allows me to relate to those who I&amp;nbsp;criticize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, over the next while (I&amp;#8217;m not sure how long it will be&amp;#8212;it depends on
how good I am at keeping up with this blog I suppose) I will be writing
blog posts about various topics which should be of some interest to
socialists, or anyone who follows politics and current events for that
matter. The first few things on my list will&amp;nbsp;be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nuclear Power: perhaps not the best choice to meet our energy needs, 
but not the doomsday technology so many people think it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genetically Modified Food: it has problems, but safety isn&amp;#8217;t one of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternative Medicine: I really don&amp;#8217;t know how to sum this one up 
without being downright&amp;nbsp;condescending.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climate Change: quite catastrophic enough without you making it sound&amp;nbsp;worse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conspiracy Theories: a case of critical thinking rather than science
&lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, but the process would be good for leftists to&amp;nbsp;learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fracking: aren&amp;#8217;t the extra greenhouse gas emissions enough reason not 
to do&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organic Food: no matter how good it makes you feel to buy it, evidence
of its benefits is&amp;nbsp;scarce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a leftist and reading this list, you may have a problem with
one or more of my inclusions. Well, too bad. I suggest you wait until I
write the corresponding article and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; judge. Or do some research
of your own in the meantime. If, however, you were offended by an 
omission, please note it in a comment below and remember that this list 
was not meant to be exhaustive. If I agree with what you&amp;#8217;re saying then
I might just write an article on it at some&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this series of articles will prove helpful, interesting and 
educational for you. Even if you aren&amp;#8217;t expecting much, do try to 
approach them with an open mind; just not so open that your brain falls&amp;nbsp;out!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Science for Socialists"></category><category term="Nuclear Power"></category><category term="GMOs"></category><category term="Alternative Medicine"></category><category term="Climate Change"></category><category term="Fracking"></category></entry><entry><title>Markov Chains and Gay Dating</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/markov-chains-and-gay-dating.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-02T13:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-07-02:markov-chains-and-gay-dating.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, in case you didn&amp;#8217;t realize, dating when you&amp;#8217;re gay is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Not to say 
it&amp;#8217;s easy for straight people, but at least you know that, when you talk to
someone, the odds are that they at least have a compatible sexuality. Not to mention that&lt;br /&gt;
when you&amp;#8217;re gay and want something serious you have to deal with the fact that
a lot of guys out there just want casual sex. This, it seems, is especially true
online and in gay bars. Some days it feels like I must be the only
gay guy in the city who actually wants a committed, monogamous&amp;nbsp;relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, however it was pointed out to me that part of the reason it can
feel that way is because those who want serious (read, monogamous) 
relationships will tend to find each
other and drop out of the dating pool&amp;#8212;at least temporarily. Or, given my 
science background, I prefer to think back to my high school chemistry classes
and say that they precipitate out of the solution. (Actually, given the effect 
that this has on the reaction&amp;#8217;s rate and equilibrium, this might be a surprisingly
apt analogy.) Thus it will
seems as though there are artificially few gay men seeking what I want. Of 
course, being someone who likes things to be quantitative, I wasn&amp;#8217;t entirely 
satisfied with such a qualitative explanation. I found myself wondering how
dramatic was this affect and just how much it could bias what I&amp;nbsp;see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I remembered some concepts from my linear algebra classes that I thought
would be useful in evaluating these questions. Taking out my old textbook, I
quickly found that what I wanted are called Markov Chains. To quote the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain"&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;, a Markov Chain&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230; a mathematical system that undergoes transitions from one state to 
another, between a finite or countable number of possible states. It is a 
random process usually characterized as memoryless: the next state depends 
only on the current state and not on the sequence of events that preceded&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, we will assume that there are only threes
states for gay&amp;nbsp;males:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interested in hookups&amp;nbsp;(A)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interested in a serious relationship&amp;nbsp;(B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a serious relationship&amp;nbsp;(C)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously a gross oversimplification. In the future I may well add more
categories. There are various other problems which will become apparent as we
work through this simple analysis; I will point them out as we get to&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Markov Chains can be represented by graphics such as the one below:
&lt;img alt="There are three circles, representing the three groups, with paths connecting them. On each path is a probability of someone following that path between time steps." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/markovDating.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The label &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{XY}\)&lt;/span&gt; next to each of the arrows is the probability that a member
of group X will move to group Y over some time-period&amp;#8212;say, one month. These 
probabilities can be represented by the following&amp;nbsp;matrix: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P = \begin{bmatrix} 
P_{AA} &amp;amp; P_{BA} &amp;amp; P_{CA} \\\\\\\\
P_{AB} &amp;amp; P_{BB} &amp;amp; P_{CB} \\\\\\\\
P_{AC} &amp;amp; P_{BC} &amp;amp; P_{CC} 
\end{bmatrix} .$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some population of gay men then you can represent the number of men
in each group as a&amp;nbsp;vector 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\vec{N_0} = \left( \begin{array}{c} A_0 \\\\\\\\ B_0 \\\\\\\\ C_0 \end{array} \right).$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The number of people in each group after one month would then be given&amp;nbsp;by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\vec{N_1} = P \vec{N_0}.$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; More&amp;nbsp;generally, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\vec{N_{n+1}} = P \vec{N_n}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
implying&amp;nbsp;that &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\vec{N_k} = P^{k} \vec{N_0}.$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; One of the properties of the 
matrix representations of Markov Chains is&amp;nbsp;that &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\lim_{k \to \infty} P^{k}$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
converges to some matrix &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(L\)&lt;/span&gt; which represents the system&amp;#8217;s equilibrium state. The
columns of the matrix will all be the same vector, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\vec{x}\)&lt;/span&gt;, known as the
steady-state probability vector. This represents the fraction of people
in each group once the system has reached its steady-state. It follows that
the system will eventually reach this configuration no matter what the
starting&amp;nbsp;conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we&amp;#8217;ve set up a simple model of the gay dating scene. But, before I 
continue, I need to highlight a weakness of this model; it doesn&amp;#8217;t (explicitly) 
account for age-groups. It can not  account for people&amp;#8217;s attitudes changing as t
hey mature or for the entrance of new, younger
people into the dating pool. This has an impact on what values we choose when
filling our matrix. For example, my suspicion is that many guys who are 
initially into hookups will, after having had their fun and with some increased
maturity, become tired of 
them and want a more serious relationship. However, in the real world, this
may be offset by new people entering the dating pool. None of this can be directly
modelled here, which is a weakness of these simple
Markov Chains. If I decide to continue this sort of analysis in future, it
would suggest that I should abandon them in favour of a more complex model. 
For the purposes of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; article, let&amp;#8217;s just assume that the
people in the dating pool don&amp;#8217;t mature or alter their attitudes. This is
almost certainly wrong, but it would require a far more complicated model, in
which the various probabilities depended not only on someone&amp;#8217;s current 
relationship status but also on their relationship history, to overcome this&amp;nbsp;limitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these simplifications, let&amp;#8217;s see what assumptions we can reasonably make 
about the value of our &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P\)&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;matrix:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone who seeks hookups will not start looking for a relationship. 
(&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{AB} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasionally a hookup will turn into a relationship. (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{AC} &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone who wants a relationship will not change to wanting hookups. 
(&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{BA} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationship generally last more than one iteration of the model. 
(&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{CC} &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a someone gets out of a relationship they will seek another relationship
and not hookups. (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P_{CA} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last assumption is the one which strikes me as the most inaccurate, as 
someone who entered a relationship via a hookup would probably go back to 
hookups and someone who gets out of a long-term relationship might want to 
partake in hookups for a little while before looking for a new relationship.
However, to properly account for these things would require me to know the
history of the system, which would mean I could no longer use a simple Markov&amp;nbsp;Chain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can now start filling in the&amp;nbsp;matrix:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P = \begin{bmatrix} 
1 - P_{AC} &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\\\\\\\
0 &amp;amp; 1 - P_{BC} &amp;amp; 1 - P_{CC} \\\\\\\\
P_{AC} &amp;amp; P_{BC} &amp;amp; P_{CC} 
\end{bmatrix} .$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s say that each iteration of the model corresponds to one month. 
Furthermore, let&amp;#8217;s assume that someone seeking hookups has an ~1% chance of 
ending up in a relationship over the course of a year, or a 0.1% chance of ending
up in a relationship each month. We&amp;#8217;ll assume that the probability of a 
relationship lasting one year is ~50%, ie: there is a 94% chance they will last
each month. These are numbers which I essentially made up, but they seem
reasonable to me. Unfortunately, I have no idea what the odds are of someone 
entering a relationship each month. I&amp;#8217;ll just guess and say 5% (which 
corresponds to an ~45% probability of entering a relationship over the course
of a year).&amp;nbsp;Thus: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$P = \begin{bmatrix} 
.999 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\\\\\\\
0 &amp;amp; .95 &amp;amp; .06 \\\\\\\\
.001 &amp;amp; .05 &amp;amp; .94 
\end{bmatrix} .$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/octave/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNU&lt;/span&gt; Octave&lt;/a&gt; software (an open
source clone of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MATLAB&lt;/span&gt;), I computed  &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(P^{k}\)&lt;/span&gt; using larger and larger values
of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; until the results converged on some matrix &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(L\)&lt;/span&gt;, as described above. This
didn&amp;#8217;t happen until &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k \approx 13000\)&lt;/span&gt;. That is to say, it took this system
1083 years to reach equilibrium. I think it is safe to say that my assumption
of people in the model not maturing as I iterate the model
is pretty invalid! For those that are curious, the steady-state probability
vector&amp;nbsp;is 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;$$\vec{x} = \left( \begin{array}{c}0 \\\\\\\\
0.55 \\\\\\\\
0.45\end{array} \right).$$&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more meaningful thing to do would be to look at how the number of people in
each group changes over time. In my current city there are probably around 
30,000 post-secondary students during the school year. Assuming that half of
them are male and that 5% of males are gay, that works out to 750 young gay
men. We&amp;#8217;ll assume that initially none of them are in a relationship, that half
of them are interested in hookups, and that half of them want a relationship.
The number of people in each relationship is shown in the graph below over a
period of four&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Group A appears to decrease more or less linearly in size, Group B decreases rapidly at first and then levels off, and Group C increases quickly at first before levelling off." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/markovRes.png" /&gt; At the end of the four year period, there are 357 people looking for hookups, 
213 peoples looking for a relationship, and 180 people in a relationship. Even
though half of the population (and increasing) is long-term-relationship 
oriented, these people make up only 37% of the dating pool. I&amp;#8217;d be very 
interested to know how closely this corresponds to reality. Of course, 
evaluating reality
is made more complicated by things like open relationships and people who are
seeking a relationship but will partake in hookups in the&amp;nbsp;meantime. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, according to this model, it turns out that those seeking a relationship
will, four years in, be in a minority within the dating pool so long as initially
more than 37% of people are interested in hookups. So this
tends to indicate what I suspected&amp;#8212;even though it might feel like you&amp;#8217;re alone in
seeking a long-term gay relationship, there is a good chance that the majority
of gay guys actually share your views. Now the only problem is finding&amp;nbsp;them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    var location_protocol = (false) ? 'https' : document.location.protocol;
    if (location_protocol !== 'http' &amp;&amp; location_protocol !== 'https') location_protocol = 'https:';
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = location_protocol + '//cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="Dating"></category><category term="Markov Chains"></category><category term="Mathematics"></category><category term="Mathematical Models"></category></entry><entry><title>The Mathematics of Protest</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/the-mathematics-of-protest.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-30T18:16:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-06-30:the-mathematics-of-protest.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy reading about how math can be applied to predicting societal
actions. I&amp;#8217;m not quite sure why. Perhaps it just makes me think of Isaac 
Asimov&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychohistory_(fictional)"&gt;psychohistory&lt;/a&gt;. In any case, I read a very interesting &lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21829234.300-brazil-uprising-points-to-rise-of-leaderless-networks.html?cmpid=RSS|NSNS|2012-GLOBAL|online-news#.UdCUB6BhLCe"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; 
in &lt;em&gt;New Scientist&lt;/em&gt; magazine the other day
which gave a mathematical and statistical examination of protest, in particular
the recent protests in Brazil. It discussed how this sort of unrest spreads
in much the same way as diseases and forest fires. Once something starts off
the unrest (in the Brazilian case, an increase in bus fairs), 
unrelated long-time grievances can come to the fore and cause 
surprising amounts of civil disobedience that can persist even after the
original issue is dealt with. Frankly, I&amp;#8217;m surprised that you&amp;#8217;d
need a mathematical model to know that; to anyone who&amp;#8217;s studied history
it should be common&amp;nbsp;sense. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting statement that was made is that
it is the &amp;#8220;newly prosperous,&amp;#8221; afraid of losing their new found success, who tend to be protesting. It reminds me of what
one of my high school history teachers used to say about revolutions: you 
don&amp;#8217;t get revolutions when people have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; hope but when you &lt;em&gt;give&lt;/em&gt; them hope and
then try to take it away. Rabble-raisers everywhere take&amp;nbsp;note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other factors which were noted to facilitate the spread of protest include high food prices, high
numbers of unemployed young people, and access to  social media. The latter-most 
is said to &amp;#8220;boost a protest&amp;#8217;s transmission rate through susceptible societies.&amp;#8221;
I wonder if, perhaps, part of the reason why youth are more likely to spread
civil unrest is because they are more adept at using social media? It is also
speculated that recent protests relate to a societal trend away from hierarchy 
and towards more horizontalist means of&amp;nbsp;organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing which irked me about the article was that it had a somewhat
condescending tone towards protesters. Notice how it compared the spread of
protests to the spread of diseases. While perhaps mathematically accurate, that is not a pleasant comparison, is it? Of course,
as a socialist with a somewhat revolutionary bend, I suppose I hold an
unusually positive view on&amp;nbsp;protest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something which worries me a little bit is
whether this sort of knowledge could be used to suppress protest and dissent. 
I can certainly imagine governments &lt;em&gt;wanting&lt;/em&gt; to do that.
For those of us wanting to change the world, it would be a very large 
impediment if the ruling classes used mathematics and sociology to try to
enforce the status quo. Of course, a different approach would be for them to 
attempt to understand the root cause of unrest and to fix it. Would this be a
good thing? It would certainly improve the lives of people in the short term. 
But would it be demobilizing? Would we not just end up with a
friendlier, reformed version of the world we live in today, with all of the old 
class structures still intact? In effect, would it simply lead to a redoing of
Keynesian social democracy? I&amp;#8217;ll leave that debate aside for now. In any case,
I suspect that it is irrelevant: the response of the ruling class to Occupy Wall
Street seems to show a complete disinterest in appeasement. And, in any case,
Keynesian policies failed once and would almost certainly fail if tried&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we must ask ourselves, how is this information useful to activists and 
to the people who organize these protests? Can it inform our strategies and
tactics? Can we use it to our advantage? Is 
it ethical to do so? After all, you&amp;#8217;d essentially be manipulating people. I
suppose my view is that this sort of research will allow activists to anticipate
if a protests will become widespread. This will allow us radicals to be prepared
somewhat in advance. For those who work on theoretical analysis, research such
as this may lend a mathematical or even an empirical basis for what at present 
feels at times like nothing more that intuition and vague guess. That is when
I&amp;#8217;ll be convinced that we have truly &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_socialism"&gt;Scientific Socialism&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mathematics"></category><category term="Protest"></category><category term="Activism"></category><category term="Brazil"></category></entry></feed>