<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Political Physicist</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://politicalphysicist.github.io/</id><updated>2015-07-10T23:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Tsipras, go to Hell</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/tsipras-go-to-hell.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-10T23:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-07-10T23:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2015-07-10:tsipras-go-to-hell.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit: Once the initial disappointment was over, I was able to step back and
appreciate that this was a rather infantile post. While I stand by my comments
that Tsipras was naive and feel that, if they weren’t going to use it to fight
back against the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EU&lt;/span&gt;, calling the referendum was ultimately harmful because of
the ensuing economic turmoil, name calling such as this is
not very helpful. On the other hand, I don’t wish to erase history, so I have
decided to leave the post up, but with this disclaimer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;January 21, 2016&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s come to this. After my fierce criticism a
&lt;a href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/greeks-bearing-debts.html"&gt;few weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;,
Greek prime minister Alexis Tsipras briefly managed to redeem himself somewhat
in my opinion by calling a referendum on the (incredibly bad) deal which Greece
had been offered and asking people to vote “no” (“oxi,” in Greek). As the
population was scared of the possibility of being forced out of the Euro,
everyone expected the result to be close and no one was sure which way it would
go. Much to everyone’s surprise, Greeks gave “oxi” a landslide victory of over
60%. Finally, I thought, Tsipras might actually play hardball with Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="One of the few remotely unflattering pictures of Greek PM Alexis Tsipras" src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/tsipras-bad-photo.jpg"/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;One of the few remotely unflattering pictures of Greek &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PM&lt;/span&gt; Alexis Tsipras&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Europe took no notice. They
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jul/07/greece-crisis-eurozone-tsipras-banking-collapse"&gt;told him&lt;/a&gt;
he had until midnight Wednesday
to submit a “credible” proposal for a deal, or Europe would begin preparing
for Greece’s departure from the Eurozone (the so-called “Grexit”).
So now Tsipras has
&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2015/jul/09/greece-debt-crisis-athens-accepts-harsh-austerity-as-bailout-deal-nears"&gt;submitted a proposal&lt;/a&gt;
for a deal that is objectively worse than the one rejected in the referendum. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot that I could say about this. I could mention how incredibly
naive Tsipras and the leadership of his party (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt;) were. I could mention
how incompetent there were when it came to planning for other eventualities.
I could question why they even held a referendum if this was to be the result.
But I’m too frustrated to form a coherent blog post about that. In any case, it
has already been said by others, both
&lt;a href="https://www.jacobinmag.com/2015/07/tsipras-syriza-greece-euro-debt/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SYRIZA&lt;/span&gt; members&lt;/a&gt;
and international
&lt;a href="http://www.leninology.co.uk/2015/07/syriza-defeat-victory-defeat.html"&gt;sympathizers&lt;/a&gt;.
What I have to say is much simpler, far more puerile, and infinitely more satisfying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alexis Tsipras, go to Hell! Seriously, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUCK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OFF&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HELL&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YOU&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUCKING&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QUISLING&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BASTARD&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want you to starve to death on the poverty income
that nearly half of all Greek pensioners are receiving. I want you to feel
the despair and hopelessness which has caused a
&lt;a href="http://www.cnbc.com/2015/02/04/greek-austerity-sparks-sharp-rise-in-suicides.html"&gt;35% increase in suicides&lt;/a&gt;
since the beginnings of austerity. I want you to go down in history as a traitor
to your cause, more reviled by your party than even
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramsay_MacDonald"&gt;Ramsay MacDonald&lt;/a&gt; was in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may well be true that the situation is complex and there are reasons for
what you did. But I don’t care. I want you chained to a rock where buzzards
will peck out your liver each morning for the rest of eternity. Or perhaps you
could be made to push a bolder up a hill every day, only to have it roll back
down just before reaching the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barring that, I at least want you kicked out of your party and force from office.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Austerity"></category><category term="Greece"></category><category term="SYRIZA"></category><category term="Alexis Tsipras"></category><category term="Rant"></category></entry><entry><title>The Rights and Wrongs of Remembrance</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/the-rights-and-wrongs-of-remembrance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-09T11:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-11-09T11:20:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2014-11-09:the-rights-and-wrongs-of-remembrance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s that time of year again. 95 years and 362 days ago we saw the
Armistice that ended World War I. This marked the end of the first case
technological war, which caused the world to realize the horrors that could
be inflicted by industrial-scale killing. It was a horrible, pointless
event in which some 16 million people lost their lives. The world, including
the victors, reacted in horror to what they had unleashed. We quickly saw the
establishment of Remembrance Day, to commemorate the tragedy, and the red poppy
as a symbol of remembrance. Of course, as we all know, this was followed two
decades later by another, even worse, case of mass slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to identify as a moderate pacifist. I’m not an absolute pacifist like
Gandhi was; I think that violence is justified if it is absolutely necessary for
self-defence. I will reluctantly admit that we probably did have to fight in
World War &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;, such was the threat of Hitler.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But I do not believe that the
First World War was in any way necessary or justifiable. Moreover, I would argue
that the Second World War was ultimately the result of how Germany was treated
in the Treaty of Versaille and was thus, ultimately, avoidable. As for
subsequent wars in which we’ve been involved: I can’t honestly say that I would
consider them much (if any) better than World War I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My relative pacifism results in my having rather ambivalent feelings towards
Remembrance Day. These are difficult to put into words, but I’m going to try my
best here. While I certainly do think that we should remember the tragedy
that was the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WWI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WWII&lt;/span&gt;, the Korean War, the Gulf War, and Afghanistan, I must
say that I have my qualms over how this is done. We are told to be grateful to
those who made the ultimate sacrifice to preserve our freedom. But to me it
feels wrong to feel grateful to people for going off to kill and be killed.
Certainly this is the case in the First World War, where I would argue that
the Allies weren’t even that much more free than Germany; just look at the
treatment of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene_V._Debs#Arrest_and_imprisonment"&gt;Eugene Debs&lt;/a&gt;
in the United States. But even in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WWII&lt;/span&gt;, the most that I can say for those
who went off for war is that their actions were necessary but unfortunate and
tragic. To say that I am grateful for those actions would make it sound like I’m
celebrating them, which I emphatically do not want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been told by one person that we should respect the fact that these soldiers
were, rightly or wrongly, willing to give up their lives for their country. But
why? We don’t celebrate, in and of itself, the fact that people are willing to
give up their lives for their convictions. We only celebrate that sort of
martyrdom of we happen to agree with the convictions. We don’t celebrate suicide
bombers, after all. So I’m not willing simply to celebrate that soldiers were
brave enough to go off to battle. Even if we justify their actions by saying that
they were misled, I still don’t think that justifies any feelings of gratitude.
Pity, perhaps, but not gratitude. I can’t even bring myself to feel respect for 
that, as doing so feels like it would be to endorse uncritical obedience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I’m saying is that Remembrance Day asks us to celebrate the
sacrifices made by soldiers without ever questioning why those sacrifices were
made. It assumes that the wars in which we engaged were just. Worse still, it
often becomes a celebration of military history. In Canada in particular, we are
told about how the battles at Passchendaele and Vimy Ridge saw the “birth of a
nation.” Well, the Canada that I would consider to be my country (if that
idealized country has ever actually existed) was not born in any battle.
It was born in the
establishment of trade unions, the development of our shared public
infrastructure, the creation of medicare, our rejection of the
war in Vietnam and later Iraq,&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the writing of the Charter of Rights and
Freedoms. I think that most Canadians perceive ourselves as being fairly peaceful,
nonviolent people. So why should we consider these battles to be the birth of our
nation? Why should a military event be given such an important role in our history
when the Armed Forces play such a small role in our culture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my bigger problem with Remembrance Day is how it relates to the wars that are
going on now. There is, of course, a “support our troops” message. Now, one could
argue that even this is objectionable, as the Armed Forces are basically salaried
killers. I’m not going to get into that here. In any case, no matter what my
objections may be to the Armed Forces, I’d still like to see the troops come home
safely. In fact, to me, the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way that you can support our troops is to
demand that they come home. But “support our troops” always seems to have a strong
subtext of “support our wars.” When I was in grade 9,
my school attended a “support our troops” rally rather than having our own
Remembrance Day ceremony. I think this was related to the fact that an alumnus had
recently been killed in Afghanistan. We were assured by the principal that this
was distinct from supporting our war. Seven years on, I can’t remember exactly
what was said at the rally. But I do recall it being emphasized how brave and noble
the soldiers were being. And I distinctly remember feeling that I had been
duped into attending a pro-war event. That, to me, is not an appropriate way to
commemorate the ending of World War I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that, rather than being a time to mourn the horrendous loss of life that
we see in modern warfare, Remembrance Day has become a time when we are meant to
celebrate the sacrifices of soldiers, past and present. Implicit to this
celebration is the idea that their violence was justified. Consider “In Flanders
Field.” I don’t think that there is a single Remembrance Day ceremony, anywhere
in Canada, where that poem isn’t read. But think about the last stanza:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take up our quarrel with the foe:&lt;br/&gt;
To you from failing hands we throw&lt;br/&gt;
   The torch; be yours to hold it high.&lt;br/&gt;
   If ye break faith with us who die &lt;br/&gt;
We shall not sleep, though poppies grow&lt;br/&gt;
        In Flanders fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s asking us to continue fighting. Not to realize the folly of war and lay down
our arms, but to persist with it. What’s more, it was written during World War I,
which was a pointless war between imperialist powers. Canadian soldiers &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; no
quarrel with German soldiers and I consider them just as worthy of our
remembrance. But I don’t recall that ever being mentioned at any of the numerous
Remembrance Day ceremonies that I have attended over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A white and a red poppy." src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/poppies.jpg"/&gt;
All of these feelings are the reason why I haven’t made it a point to wear a
poppy in recent years. To be clear, it’s not that I specifically avoid wearing
a poppy. It’s just that I haven’t had one with me in Halifax and haven’t made it
a point to buy one. I’ve been thinking for awhile that I should get my hands on a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_poppy"&gt;white poppy&lt;/a&gt;. It seems that it would
more accurately convey my mixed feelings about Remembrance Day. I know that many
veterans find it offensive and I regret causing offence. However, if they find
the idea of denouncing the violence of the wars they fought in offensive, then
they are in the wrong and I would not censor myself for their sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess the point that I’m trying to make is: at 11:&lt;span class="caps"&gt;00AM&lt;/span&gt; on November the 11&lt;sup&gt;
th&lt;/sup&gt; we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; remember everyone who has suffered in war. But I do mean
everyone. We should remember the Canadian and American and British soldiers who
fell. We should remember those who lived, but with both mental and physical injury.
We should remember the German and Austrian and Italian soldiers. And we should
remember the civilians who died as armies marched across the world and bombs
fell from the skies. We should remember how horrific war was. We should remember
why war should never be allowed to happen again. Lest we forget…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do, however, have a lot of respect for the pacifists within the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CCF&lt;/span&gt; (the more radical predecessor to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt;) who argued in parliament against our involvement in World War &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;. It’s certainly a far cry from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt;’s support, a few years ago, for bombing Libya. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both of these were only partial objections. We, unfortunately, did provide support for the Americans—we just never actually engaged in battle. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Pacifism"></category><category term="Remembrance Day"></category><category term="Poppies"></category></entry><entry><title>10 Reasons I Sometimes Hate Being a Socialist</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/10-reasons-i-sometimes-hate-being-a-socialist.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-15T09:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-06-15T09:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2014-06-15:10-reasons-i-sometimes-hate-being-a-socialist.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you might have gathered from my blog posts here, I am pretty left wing.
You know you’re pretty radical when you have to preface any explanation of
your beliefs with “Well, I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; consider myself a communist.”
And, while I am quite confidant in the validity of my beliefs, there are days
when I really wish that I didn’t have them. So, without further ado, here
are the top 10 reasons I wish I wasn’t a socialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. The exhaustion of trying to stick to the moral high-ground.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one would ever be a socialist in the West if they didn’t believe that
there was a moral force behind it. Not only does socialism mean that you end
up fighting a thankless, apparently losing battle, but also that you’re trying
to live by a set of principles that can seem impossible under our current
system. For example, how am I supposed to find clothes that I know weren’t made
in sweatshops? How do you live an environmentally-friendly lifestyle in cities
designed around the car? How do you fight patriarchy when even your friends
sometimes say derogatory things about women?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the more abstract level, it’s exhausting trying to explain all of this to
friends. And what do you do about that slight feeling of disapproval when they
don’t live up to your moral standards? Judging people is not only unpleasant,
but also quite tiresome as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. I am perpetually angry.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sticking to your moral principles also tends to make you distinctly unhappy
about the state of the world around you.
Seeing as socialism has been suffering almost nothing but defeats for the
past 30 years, just about anything that happens in politics will be bad news
for me. I swear, government policy seems almost specifically tailored to piss
me off, whether it’s cuts in services, cuts in taxes, support for foreign
interventions, failure to tackle climate change, rolling back of labour rights,
privatization, or what. The wonderfully pessimistic left-wing British
comedian Jeremy Hardy sums it up well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All socialists have bad backs because we slouch—except when we’re watching
the news when we sit on the edge of our seats, shout, and wave our arms.
Generally we sit hunched, arms crossed in a judgemental way, the whole of
our bodies pulled into a frown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. I get to listen to people’s ignorant statements about socialism.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the horrors inflicted in Eastern Europe in the name of socialism,
various people will insist that socialism is an inherently bloody and evil
philosophy or that when I advocate something like redistributive taxes (let
alone start talking about the long list of industries that I’d like to
see nationalized) I am advocating
gulags.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; No less irritating are people who say that socialism inevitably
leads to a situation like the one in Greece. Don’t these people realize that
Greece is an example of a welfare state (albeit a highly dysfunctional one),
not a socialist economy in which the means of production are held in common?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Having to hold back when discussing politics.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as those who know me well can attest, I’m not actually very good at this.
But there are many situations in which I do try because, if I were to say what
I actually thought, people would think that I was crazy. When I do fully speak
my mind, at least to someone who is also political, I will often end up in
arguments. Which is never a fun thing and tends to leave me feeling perturbed
for a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Looking  at the world in a fundamentally different way than others.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things which makes political discussions so difficult for me is that
the set of assumptions I go in with are different from those of just about
everyone else. Of course, the main one is that I don’t assume that capitalism
is the only option out there. This means that the range of policies I consider
are not as constrained as for most people. For example, if someone argues
that we can’t pursue some regulation because it would cause investment to dry
up, then I’d suggest nationalizing the banks so that there is public control
over investment. If a policy has the risk of causing a business to leave the
country, then place the business under worker’s control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are also more subtle things at play here. Socialists often have a
different interpretation of history than the conventional one. While I think
that this is a more accurate interpretation and provides a much better
explanation of the world, it does make discussing history with other people
more difficult because there is less common ground between us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. The difficulty introduced when trying to date.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this makes meeting people any easier. It can make things
awkward enough among friends. But when you’re trying to date it makes things
harder still. Politics, after all, does not make a great thing to discuss on
a date, especially when your politics are rather unusual. But there’s also the
fact that if I’m in a relationship I’d like it to be with someone who broadly
shares the same values that I do. I don’t think this is unreasonable, surely?
The problem is, most people are either unpolitical (in which case one of my
major interests is off the table to talk about) or have considerably more
moderate views than mine. Oh well, probably someday I’ll meet a nice liberal
or social democrat who can put up with my radicalism. Because that seems
considerably more likely than my finding another socialist that I’d get along
with well enough to want to date.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Which leads on to my next point…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Having to put up with other socialists.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there’s a whole article’s worth of stuff I could say about this one.
There’s the fact that most socialists seem to end up taking irrational views
on things like nuclear energy, genetically modified foods, and any number
of other things. Similarly, there’s the general lack of knowledge about
science and critical thinking, the consequent inability to come to informed
conclusions, and the stupidity that results when dealing with many contemporary
issues (although, in fairness, I think that most ideological groups are
guilty of this). There’s the sectarianism which means that, in many countries,
you have nearly as many socialist parties as there are socialists. And finally
there is the bohemian weirdness and alternative lifestyle &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BS&lt;/span&gt; that seems so
pervasive. You know what? I don’t particularly want to live in a commune! I
admit that I’m sexually repressed and I don’t have a problem with that!
I’m happy being constrained to a monogamistic paradigm within relationships!
I don’t think that marriage is inherently patriarchal and, yes, I would even
like to get married myself some day!
I don’t feel the need to take mind-altering drugs, smoke pot, dye my hair a
funny colour, grow a beard, eschew going to the barber’s shop, get piercings,
or have sex with anyone I find remotely attractive! I know that not all
socialists correspond to the straw-man that I’ve constructed, but enough of
them do for me to find it off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my feelings can be summed up quite well by something that
Orwell&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; wrote in &lt;em&gt;The Road to Wigan Pier&lt;/em&gt;: “As with the
Christian religion, the worst advertisement for Socialism is its adherents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. Feeling faintly embarrassed of my beliefs.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because there are so many socialists that display the (in my mind)
disreputable qualities listed above, I find myself feeling embarrassed to be
associated with them. How can socialism ever be taken seriously if these are
the sorts of people representing it? Once again, I think Orwell says it best
when he wrote that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this there is the horrible—the really
disquieting—prevalence of cranks wherever Socialists are gathered together.
One sometimes gets the impression that the mere words “Socialism” and
“Communism” draw towards them with magnetic force every fruit-juice drinker,
nudist, sandal-wearer, sex-maniac, Quaker, “Nature Cure” quack, pacifist,
and feminist in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I want to make it absolutely clear that I think it is totally unfair
to lump feminists, pacifists, and even Quakers into the same group as the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;9. Not being politically “out” to my family.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere is this embarrassment more apparent than when it comes to my family.
I’d never feel comfortable showing them the sort of people and writings
produced by many in the socialist movement. And this certainly isn’t helped
by the fact that my family is a good deal more conservative than me.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
My parents are essentially small-l liberals. On the one hand they support
regulation and things like universal health care, but on the other they
certainly wouldn’t be in favour of the sorts of nationalizations that I call
for and they are vehemently anti-union. What’s more, my dad is a business
owner. These are hardly people that I can talk to about the ills of capitalism.
So I’m never entirely honest with them when it comes to politics and I end
up hiding this part of myself from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10. Always being on the losing side.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve stated above, the last thirty years have seen little but defeat for
socialist ideas. One only needs to look at the recent Ontario election to see
how far to the right things have shifted: the Conservatives were advocating
massive tax cuts and the laying-off of 100 thousand public-sector workers, 
yet they were taken seriously! Meanwhile, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt; was essentially campaigning on
anti-tax policies! How does the Left even begin to fight when even our more
moderate ideas, like tax-and-spend policies, seem so alien to the electorate?
How do we keep going when
we are shunned by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDP&lt;/span&gt;, ignored by the Liberals, and taunted by the
Conservatives? How do you keep fighting when every left-wing government
seems to end up giving in, at least partially, to capitalism? How do you
retain hope as things seem to get inexorably worse?&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have the answers to all of that. But I still feel that humanity &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt;
be capable of something better than what we have right now. If no one fights
for that then it definitely won’t happen. If we do fight, then at least we
stand a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my rebuttal to this, see my earlier post, &lt;a href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/on-socialists-and-scotsmen.html"&gt;On Socialists and Scotsmen&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to say it’s impossible. I can think of one socialist with whom I get along well. It’s a pity that she’s female. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who was a socialist, just one firmly opposed to Stalinism. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that that’s hard. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize that this is quite a different tone than I ended on a few weeks back in &lt;a href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/on-europe-the-left-and-the-future.html"&gt;On Europe, the Left, and the Future&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I was just in a better mood that day. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Politics"></category><category term="Socialism"></category></entry><entry><title>A Bit of News</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/a-bit-of-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-02T14:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-02T14:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2014-01-02:a-bit-of-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, there have been several blog articles released at the same time,
today. If you looked carefully, you may have noticed that these have actually been written
an various days over the past couple of weeks, but have only now become available online.
I feel an explaination for this erratic behaviour is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before I went home for Christmas, the &lt;a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/"&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/a&gt; 
on which I host this blog decided
that it wanted to be difficult. For whatever reason, it refused to start and I couldn’t figure
out how to fix it before it was time to leave. However, Christmas break also gave me a chance
to actually write some thoughtful blog entries, which I haven’t had time to do for awhile. So
I wrote away, unable to post them. Upon getting back to Halifax, the Raspberry Pi decided
that it was willing to work again, for some reason known only to itself. And thus I have been
able to post my blog entries. I apologize for the glut of writing after so long without any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, while I’m writing this, I might as well draw your attention to a new link at the top
of this page entitled &lt;a href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/pages/software.html"&gt;Software&lt;/a&gt;. This takes you to a page
containing useful pieces of software which I have modified or built for myself, which you
are welcome to download. Please note, however, that some of these are only set up to work
on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Thoughts"></category><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Software"></category></entry><entry><title>Insomnia Sucks</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/insomnia-sucks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-14T02:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2013-11-14T02:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-11-14:insomnia-sucks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s been awhile since I’ve written one of these. It’s not that I haven’t had
things to write about: the stress of school, post office privatization, derailments 
and scandal at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CN&lt;/span&gt;, my ambivalence towards Remembrance Day,
my dismay at discovering that some of the political figures I liked (emphasis on the
past tense) were rather
chummy with certain dictators, an exposition on why I hold the political views I do
when it seems more and more as though I don’t actually like anyone else who shares 
them… But, alas, I’ve been busy with assignments, classes, labs, making sure that
I am fed, and preventing my apartment from becoming a complete shambles. After all
that, all I really want to do is turn my brain off for awhile—not write a few
thousand words of polemic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, I’m writing something now, at last. Nothing from the topics 
listed above.
The reasons are, respectively: no one else is interested in me grumbling, 
I’ll write about that if and when the government tries it here, 
it turns out that the story didn’t have as
interesting ramifications as I expected, it will come around again next year, I 
can’t be bothered to write something requiring that many brain cells at the moment, 
and I’m probably being too hard on my comrades.
The only reason that I’m writing right now, really, is because I can’t sleep. It’s
becoming something of a problem for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a number of years now (it first started when I was still in elementary school, I
think) I’ve had some problems getting to sleep at night. But occasionally I go 
through spells when it is especially bad. This time it started three weeks ago,
during the week when I had four midterms. Presumably it was the stress that started
it. But it’s more or less continued since then. So now I find myself in this
situation: I lie awake at night, totally incapable of getting to sleep. Then, in 
the morning, I sleep through my alarm(s), wake up at 10 o’clock (which presumably
doesn’t make it any easier to get to sleep at a reasonable hour the next night), 
have to rush
to class and skip the gym (and possibly breakfast). Then, just to add insult to 
injury, there’s a good chance
that I’ll find myself nearly falling asleep during class and I’ll definitely be 
falling asleep when I try to do assigned readings. All in all, my situation feels
a lot like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/OrYGSlEmt_I" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(John Finnemore, the guy who wrote that little song, is an incredibly funny guy
whose radio sitcom &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-ptq9jqwAoY"&gt;Cabin Pressure&lt;/a&gt; 
I would most definitely recommend.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I sit up late at night, writing inanely about my inability to sleep. Will this be of any interest to you, dear reader? God knows. Probably not, actually, but 
insomnia or not I’m not feeling quite alert or clever enough at this time in the 
evening to write about anything more intellectual. In any case, good night.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Insomnia"></category><category term="John Finnemore"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Abuse of Exponentiation in Colloquial Communication</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/on-the-abuse-of-exponentiation-in-colloquial-communication.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-29T02:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-09-29T02:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-09-29:on-the-abuse-of-exponentiation-in-colloquial-communication.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Or, to put it another way, “Why I Hate it When People Say Things ‘Grow Exponentially.’”
But hey, why say something simply when you can say it in polysyllables? In any case, 
something which I have been finding increasingly irksome is when people talk about
something “growing exponentially,” when all that they really mean is that it is
growing &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; quickly. I guess I shouldn’t really blame them for this, seeing
as it’s more the lousy math education standards which are to blame. But still, I do 
wish that they could get this in their heads: &lt;strong&gt;just because it’s growing quickly
doesn’t mean that it’s growing exponentially!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Plot of exponential growth as compared to other forms of growth" src="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/images/exponential.png"/&gt;Let 
me back up a bit. For those of you with a bit of mathematical or scientific
background this will be review, but I’ll include it in case of the unlikely even
that there is anyone here without a second year university calculus class under 
their belt. And, given how nerdy/awesome my friends are, that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; rather unlikely. 
Exponential
growth refers to something that, over some fixed interval, will increase in size by
some constant factor. For example, if the water in my sink is getting higher 
exponentially, that means it starts off at, say, 1cm deep. After a minute it is 
2cm deep. After another minute it is 4cm deep. After another minute it is 8cm deep.
Pretty soon my whole apartment will be full of water, the landlord will be 
asking some difficult questions, and I’ll be wishing that I’d chosen a drier example
with which to make my point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A related concept is exponential decay. This is essentially the same thing, except
here the quantity &lt;em&gt;decreases&lt;/em&gt; by some constant factor. For example,
say I have a chocolate bar with eight segments and in the first minute I eat half 
of it (four pieces). Wanting to savour
it, over the next minute I eat half of the remaining chocolate, or two pieces. 
Wanting to stretch out my chocolate still longer, the next minute I eat only 1 piece.
The next minute I eat only half a piece. This process continues and I never actually
finish the chocolate bar. Of course, this example is totally unrealistic:
in reality I would have eaten the whole chocolate bar within the first minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, the never-quite-vanishing chocolate bar exhibits exponential behaviour,
while most things that people &lt;em&gt;call&lt;/em&gt; exponential do not. The thing about exponential 
growth is that
it tends to explode; it will eventually start growing so quickly that it just can’t
continue. Take population growth, for example. Populations are often thought of as growing
exponentially. But this can not last forever. Eventually there won’t be enough food and 
the population will level off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I see something referred to as “increasing exponentially,” my immediate reaction
is to ask for a plot of the data or the chi-squared value for an exponential fit. For 
reasons that I explained above, it is almost certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; growing exponentially. It
might be growing quickly, but that is not at all the same thing. So please, spare us
neurotic math-geeks a bit of unnecessary squirming and describe the trend properly.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Personal"></category><category term="Mathematics"></category><category term="Pet Peeve"></category></entry><entry><title>Back for Another Year of Physics and Phun</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/back-for-another-year-of-physics-and-phun.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-03T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-09-03T18:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-09-03:back-for-another-year-of-physics-and-phun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s that time of year again. The air is turning cold (or, in today’s
case, rainy), the last pay-cheque from my summer job went into my back account,
I’ve made sure I’m stocked up on all of the supplies I’ll need, and another
semester is about to start. I’ll be entering the third and penultimate year of
my astrophysics degree (my god, it’s scary how quickly the time passes). I guess
I’m supposed to be dreading this time of year, but I’m really not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a 4+ month break and now I’m sufficiently recharged to be ready to
start school again. Quite honestly, classes will be a nice change of pace, after
spending four months of writing data analysis scripts for one of my profs. Not
that there is anything wrong with doing that for a summer job—it was
a nice change from classes at the start. But, as they say, variety is the spice
of life. So learning some actual physics again, rather than just crunching
numbers, sounds good to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other reason I’m not sad that school is starting again is because my social 
life actually improves during the
semester. All of my friends in Halifax are classmates and only a few of them
were around campus over the summer. And none of them were other people from my
year. So outside of office hours (when we shouldn’t really be talking much
anyway) I had virtually no social life. Now, though, there will be plenty of
people in the physics major’s work-room (well, we get &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; work done there,
anyway) to talk to and plenty of time spent together doing homework. Honestly,
hours spent collaborating on homework sounds altogether more enjoyable than
hours spent in isolation killing time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, all things considered, I’m kind of glad that school is starting again. Just not quite as glad as I will be when it’s over come May.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="University"></category><category term="Summer"></category><category term="Physics"></category><category term="Astrophysics"></category></entry><entry><title>Take a Listen</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/take-a-listen.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-10T13:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-07-10T13:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-07-10:take-a-listen.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to discover, several months ago now, that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BBC&lt;/span&gt; had produced radio
adaptations of some of the books by my favourite author, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry_Pratchett"&gt;Terry Pratchett&lt;/a&gt;. Below is the first part of their
adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Guards! Guards!&lt;/em&gt; Take a listen!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe align="middle" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/kKhirak0QEw" width="420"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary><category term="Terry Pratchett"></category><category term="BBC"></category><category term="Radio Play"></category><category term="Guards! Guards!"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello Facebookers!</title><link href="https://politicalphysicist.github.io/hello-facebookers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-05T22:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-07-05T22:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>C. MacMackin</name></author><id>tag:politicalphysicist.github.io,2013-07-05:hello-facebookers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I’ve decided to announce this blog on Facebook. Having written two serious
posts, one of which was quite work-intensive, I figured that there wasn’t much
point in continuing if no one was going to read it. So it’s time to tell the world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit that I’m still a little bit hesitant. This blog will contain some 
rather personal information. I’ve already made my sexual
orientation quite clear on Facebook, but people wouldn’t find out unless they
actually went looking. However, now that I’ve posted a link to this blog I
will essentially have come out to the world. Not that I really mind—I’m not
at all ashamed of who I am. It’s just a bit of a big step. What’s more, this
will essentially be me officially “coming out” as a socialist. Ironically, if
anything I find that scarier. Certainly I’m not quite ready to tell my
parents &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; yet. They were fine with my being gay, but their love and support
might only go so far… I jest. Mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’ve written my previous articles it felt very much like they were going in
a diary—they were only to help organize my thoughts and no one else would ever 
read them. Now, for better or for worse, that is about to change. Or perhaps it 
won’t; I guess it all depends on how interesting people find me. I hope that
everyone out there &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; find me interesting enough to at least read some of 
what I have to say. Thank you very much for taking the time to read this far! 
Happy Friday!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Facebook"></category><category term="Blogging"></category></entry></feed>